<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second vindication of a disciplinary, anti-Erastian, orthodox free-admission to the Lords-Supper; or, The state of this controversie revised and proposed: for the fuller understanding of the most, as to the grounds whereon it stands; and more especially for the ease, and clearer proceeding of those, that shall write about it, whether for it, or against it. / By John Humfrey, min: of Froome.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86891</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3710</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1641_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209066</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867971</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867971</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170195</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86891)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170195)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 206:E1641[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second vindication of a disciplinary, anti-Erastian, orthodox free-admission to the Lords-Supper; or, The state of this controversie revised and proposed: for the fuller understanding of the most, as to the grounds whereon it stands; and more especially for the ease, and clearer proceeding of those, that shall write about it, whether for it, or against it. / By John Humfrey, min: of Froome.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 147, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by F.L. for E. Blackmore at the Angel in Pauls Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "17 June".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170195:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SECOND VINDICATION Of a Diſciplinary, Anti-<hi>Eraſtian,</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Free-admiſſion to the <hi>LORDS-S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PPER;</hi> OR, The State of this Controverſie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed and propoſed: For the fuller underſtanding of the moſt, as to the grounds whereon it ſtands; and more eſpecially for the caſe, and clearer proceeding of thoſe, that ſhall write about it, whether for it, or againſt it.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Humf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> Min: of <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oome.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ignatii Epiſt ad Philadelph.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Nos à communione quamquam prohibere non poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, niſi sponte confeſſum, aut in aliquo Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio eccleſiaſtico vel ſeculari nominatum at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victum.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Auſtin. Tom 9. lib. De Medicin. Poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tentiae, cap. 3. Ex Aquino.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>And Moſes took the blood, and sprinkled it on the people, and ſaid, Behold the blood of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which the Lord hath made with you,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Exo. 24.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>They all drank of that spiritual rock, and that rock was Chriſt.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 10.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>F. L.</hi> for <hi>E. Blackmore</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard, 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_foreword">
            <pb facs="tcp:170195:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170195:2"/>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thou haſt a deſire to ſee briefly the ſtate of my Opinion, but thinkeſt that theſe few ſheets are ſomething too long for thee to read over at once, which I would have thee to doe when thou takeſt it in hand; thou mayeſt be pleaſed if thou wilt, at thy firſt view, to wave or paſs over (with the Epiſtles wholly) the Second, Fifth, Twelfth, and Thirteenth Sections, (which are more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly polemical and the
<pb facs="tcp:170195:3"/>longeſt) and ſo both the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will lie more round in its ſelf, and thou have thy end in a trice. Only let me perſwade thee afterwards, to read the reſt in the whole together, at thy leaſure, with more delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>J. H.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170195:3"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas I underſtand by my Book-ſeller, that many doe call upon him for more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of my first little book, (which hath been ſo much oppugned) about Free-admiſsion to the Sacrament, there being now <hi>3.</hi> or <hi>4.</hi> Impreſsions out of it already, and notwithstanding my advice to the contrary, he is reſolved to make his advantage; I have thought good to take this courſe, which ſeems to me beſt; to wit, to ſet my ſelf (upon ſo much longer ſtudy on my own thoughts) to write again about as many ſheets as at firſt, and propoſe the ſame, as a ſecond Vindication of this Subject, in ſtead of the former; to the end, both that the Friends of my Opinion, may ſee more clearly into its foundations, whereon it is
<pb facs="tcp:170195:4"/>to be defended; and thoſe that will op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it, may goe about their work more dextrouſly and perſpicuouſly, having no need to uſe any bitterneſs or perſonal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions in the doing.</p>
            <p>It muſt be acknowledged that my firſt Diſcourſe about this matter being prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in two Sermons to the people, is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſuitably, that is, more popularly, and ſo the arguments may not ſeem to be ſo full and convincing, as might be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in a more large, or in a more cloſe and dry diſpute: and therefore having an occaſion ſomething too tetrically given me by Dr. <hi>Drake,</hi> a man otherwiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend, pious and learned, I thought it fit in another book, being <hi>A Rejoynder to him,</hi> to do my endeavour for the ſtrengthning and confirming what I had written, amplifying my conceptions all along, as the matter leads me on. And this book I perceive hath gained ſo much with ſome, even of my Presbyterian friends, that though they thought the firſt piece not ſo cogent, as many were apt to
<pb facs="tcp:170195:4"/>ſpeak thereof, yet they think that there is ſome ſtrength put to it herein, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particulars not unworthy conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>However this be, having ſince read <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> and ſome of his oppoſers, with a few others about this matter, I find it to be neceſſary that I ſhould deliver my mind more fully and openly as to the ſtate of the Queſtion, for the avoiding of that prejudice, which I ſee elſe by one Mr. <hi>Collings,</hi> is like to be faſten'd on me; which perſon ſpeaks of me every where in his late book about Suſpenſion, as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtus</hi> diſciple, and as if I had all out of him, which is no wayes ingenuouſly done, ſeeing I muſt profeſs really, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver once ſaw <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> until I had prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both my <hi>Vindication,</hi> and my <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſince I have ſeen him, I find the ground <hi>Eraſtus</hi> goes upon, by his firſt <hi>Theſes,</hi> lies thus, There is none ought (ſayes he, as a thing he counts ſhould be granted) to be kept from communion in
<pb facs="tcp:170195:5"/>other Ordinances, being the ordinary means to work grace in them; and for an excluſion from the Sacrament only, he ſhews there is no proof at all in Scripture, and ſo he quite takes away all Church-puniſhments. Now Dr. <hi>Drake,</hi> and thoſe that contend for a bare excluſion from actual receiving (as if Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication were nothing elſe) doe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly herein become ſemi-<hi>Eraſtian,</hi> yielding to him his very foundation, which Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> hath obſerv'd before me, <hi>Power of the Keyes, cap. 4. ſect. 43.</hi> whereas we that do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge indeed that there is no command for excluſion from the Sacrament a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, yet that the Scripture is clear for an excluſion from ſociety in general, by cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſo from the Sacrament as a part thereof, doe plainly ſtand at the greateſt elongation from <hi>Eraſtus</hi> here, and nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to the truth otherwhere (we conceive) of any. <hi>Nos</hi> (ſayes <hi>Bullinger</hi> to the point) <hi>nunquam concedere ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtis voluimus, ut diſciplinam
<pb facs="tcp:170195:5"/>et coenam commiſcerent. Coenam (docemus) eſſe publicam et laetam gratiarum actionem, et non poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam. Diſciplinam vero compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendere monitionem et correptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, adeoque poenam,</hi> Epiſt. <hi>2.</hi> ad Eraſt.</p>
            <p>Beſides Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> I know there are ſome others that have written againſt me, and it may be expected happily by ſome, that I ſhould give a particular an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to my ſeveral brethren, as I have to Mr. <hi>Drake;</hi> and I must confeſſe I have had ſome temptations thereunto, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that I had done ſomething here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in at my firſt meeting with ſome of them: But when I underſtood, that one whom I never knew, before I ſaw his firſt booke, <hi>John Timſon,</hi> had undertaken ſuch a task, I was ſoon willing to ceaſe my ſelf; for that man having given ſuch good ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to Dr. <hi>Drake</hi> and the <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter-ſhire</hi> Miniſters, in his firſt work, <hi>The Barr removed,</hi> which to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge was much taking with many plain
<pb facs="tcp:170195:6"/>judicious men, and more, I ſuppoſe to ſome, than my own; I did not doubt but we ſhould have many more good things from him in his ſecond work alſo (which hath been a while come forth,) in anſwer to Mr. <hi>Collings</hi> and Mr. <hi>Saunders.</hi> If there be any therefore who are weakned by what is ſaid in particular by any of thoſe aforeſaid oppoſers, I referr them to this Author; Of whom I ſhall think fit, in the way to ſay thus much, as what is juſt to him. He is a man, as I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, pious and ſober; One belike, that is no other for his condition, than a plain husbandman, but exemplarily ſtudious for the time he can ſpare from his daily and neceſſary labours. He was, it ſeems, bred up under the famous <hi>Robert Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and ſo one of the old Puritans, who uſing often with ſome of his neighbours to ſeek God together in the holy duty of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious conference, <hi>(Mal. 3.16.)</hi> and being deeply affected (as I ſuppoſe) with the evil of the neglect in many places of the Sacrament, (himſelf being one that
<pb facs="tcp:170195:6"/>received the firſt impreſsion of that grace which is in him, at this Ordinance) they were in the end convinced wholly of this opinion, and ſatisfied their Miniſter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame. After a while Doctor <hi>Drakes</hi> book comming out, it pleaſed God to raiſe up the ſpirit of this ſerious man, like another <hi>Amoz,</hi> as it were from the flocks, the plough and the herds, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh his thoughts about this buſineſs. I know well, that many kind of ſpirits can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but be ready to deſpiſe ſuch a one; <hi>How knoweth this man let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters?</hi> but others, happily, that are more humble and ingenuous, and no leſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, will rather be ready to bleſs God <hi>(Mat. 12.26.)</hi> to ſee what ſolidity, clearneſs of expreſsion, and eminency of gifts and piety, he is graciouſly pleaſed to ſhoud oftentimes, in ſome very mean and plain perſons.</p>
            <p>As for my ſelf, I have no deſire to draw the Sawe any more hand to hand with any in theſe perſonal conteſtations; I have thought it neceſſary to anſwer the
<pb facs="tcp:170195:7"/>chief and firſt of them that came out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, and for the reſt, I do humbly conceive, that when the ſtate of my que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is well read over in theſe few ſheets, then my <hi>Rejoynder</hi> to Dr. <hi>Drake,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thoſe few things, if you pleaſe, in the Poſtſcript Epiſtle adjoyn'd, will be enough to anſwer all (as to the main) that any other hath ſaid after him. Only it is my deſire, that thoſe who ſhall think fit to write againſt me for the future, will be pleaſed to deal principally with this laſt work, which is more digeſted and order'd for diſpute, and then to take in what I have written in my other two books (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in my <hi>Rejoynder,</hi> wherein is moſt) as it will fall in for confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and farther probation of what here is propoſed as the ſtandard to them; which if they will do candidly, as it lies in its full ſtrength, and deal with me fairly without invectives and impertinencies, they ſhall do well. For my part I have ſo prepared theſe ſheets, as nothing elſe may prevail, but plainneſs of truth and ſtrength of argument. If any ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:170195:7"/>come with expectation of expreſsions to pleaſe the fancy, they will be fruſtrated; The author deſires here both to appear himſelf without affectation, and to leave his matter wholly upon the teſt of the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without any inſinuation by the affection.</p>
            <p>There is one thing yet I have to adde upon advice, and it is this; that, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as many good men; that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, have entertained ſome prejudicate thoughts of my perſon, (very likely for my judgements ſake) whom they have not known; which hath made them weight the leſſe formerly what I have ſaid, and ſo may ſtill: I have thought good for the ſatisfying and un-bending ſuch of my Brethren, having had ſome occaſions lately to deſire the teſtimonial of my reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend neighbours in the Miniſtry to the <hi>Commiſſioners for approbation of publique Preachers</hi> about matters of my living, to ſubſcribe here their certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate; which I doubt not but they will own, to this effect. Onely with this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it be not understood, as given
<pb facs="tcp:170195:8"/>with any reference in particular to this controverſie, wherein they and I doe leave one another to our own opinions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THeſe are to certifie whom it may concern, that wee whoſe names are hereunder written, upon our perſonal acquaintance with Mr</hi> John Humfrey <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Froome, <hi>do know him to be a man Orthodox in doctrine, and Pious in his converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Richard Allen, <hi>Min: of</hi> Batcomb.</item>
               <item>Chriſtoph: Read, <hi>Min: of</hi> Wanſtrow,</item>
               <item>Rich: Fairclough, <hi>Min: of</hi> Mells,</item>
               <item>Will: Thomſon, <hi>Min: of</hi> Laverton,</item>
               <item>John Geree, <hi>Min: of</hi> Freſhford,</item>
               <item>John After, <hi>Min: of</hi> Beckington,</item>
               <item>William Parker, <hi>Min: of</hi> Bruton.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170195:8"/>
            <head>Mr. HUMFREYES FREE-ADMISSION STATED.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTION 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T has ever been the gracious appointment and will of God, to have a Church upon earth, or a certain number of men and women to be in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-relation with him, in oppoſition to others, who are ſaid to be without God, and without Chriſt in the world.</p>
               <p>Under the Old Teſtament it pleaſed the Lord to chuſe out <hi>Abraham, Iſaack, Jacob,</hi> and their poſterity, to be the lot of his inheritance, <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.26, 27. and 32.8, 9. and his peculiar people,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170195:9"/>
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.6. &amp; 14.2. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 135.4. Under the New Teſtament he hath enlarged the tents, and lengthned the cords: ſo that herein now is his glory ſhown in having multitudes, people, nations, languages, to flow in to him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 2.2, 3, 4. <hi>Behold, thou ſhalt call a nation which thou kneweſt not, and nations which knew thee not ſhall run unto thee,</hi> Iſ. 55.5. there is Gods call of a Nation, and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions anſwer to that call, which being ſpoken of Chriſt under the Goſpel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.19. is manifeſt proof for our national Churches, as others have obſerved.</p>
               <p>For as the whole people of the Jews were the Church of God, and ſo accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a holy ſeed, a choſen generation, a ſanctified people, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.2. <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.3. <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.24. Gods vine, the daughter of his people, his children, <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.1. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that every man, woman and child of them, without exception, are taken into covenant, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10, 11, 12. There were many of them ignorant perſons, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 5.13. many of them wicked perſons, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 81.11. <hi>Amos</hi> 3.2. Yet are they owned of God for his people, and ſo called his people,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170195:9"/>children of the Kingdom, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.12. children of the covenant, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.25. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.6. in reference to this cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-relation. <hi>Hear O my people, and I will teſtifie againſt thee, I am God, even thy God,</hi> Pſal. 50.7. <hi>I enter'd covenant with thee, and thou becameſt mine,</hi> Ez. 16.8. <hi>He came to his own, and his own recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him not,</hi> Jo. 1.11. they are called his own ſtill, though they refuſed him.</p>
               <p>So is it now with all thoſe Nations that having had the Goſpel preached, and anſwering to that Goſpel have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the doctrine of Chriſt, ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to his Ordinances in profeſſion of his name, they are hereby engrafted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Jews olive or covenant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17. with <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.26. and ſo to be reckoned, as they were, the people of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. Beleevers, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.12, 13. Diſciples, <hi>Jo.</hi> 6.66. Chriſtians, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.26. Saints by calling, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. the Church of the Gentiles, and Kingdom of Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.41.</p>
               <p>And to this purpoſe doe ſuch texts as theſe, <hi>Mi.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 65. 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Matt.</hi> 21.43. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 86.9. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 25.6. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 22.27. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2.8.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170195:10"/>
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (See Mr. <hi>Hudſons</hi> Vind. p. 16. and Mr. <hi>Baxt.</hi> Inf: Bap: p. 339, 340. Edit. 3.) ſpeak of the Church ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry largely and magnificently under the Goſpel. <hi>The ſame covenant,</hi> ſayes Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therford (Treat. Cov. p. 73. &amp; 343.) <hi>that was made with</hi> Abraham, <hi>is made with the</hi> Corinthians, 2 Cor. 6.16. <hi>I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people.</hi> And as that is extended to the whole Jews, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.12, 13. So are the whole Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 55.4, 5. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 60.1, 2. All Nations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.1, 2. All fleſh, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 66.23. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 40.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.2. All the kinreds of the earth, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 22.26, 27. The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the world, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. From the riſing of the Sun, to the going down thereof, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.11. (to wit, even as many of them as the Lord our God ſhall call, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.39.) ſaid to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the people of God under the New Teſtament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170195:10"/>
               <head>SECT. 2.</head>
               <p>I Know indeed, for all theſe many and arge expreſſions every where in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, ſome eminent Divines do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Church and Covenant ought to be reſtrained to the regenerate only, and that none elſe are really, but nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally &amp; aequivocally Church-members. And ſo I remember <hi>Arminius</hi> expreſſes it for them, <hi>Diſp. pub. Theſ.</hi> 18. <hi>Sec.</hi> 15. <hi>Vocati, et non electi, ad eccleſiam viſibilem pertinere judicantur, quanquam Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocè, quum ad inviſibilem non pertine ant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This doctrine enforces them to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh, between what gives right as to a mans own part unto Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip and the Ordinances, and that which gives right to be admitted; whereas the truth is, theſe are <hi>Relata, quorum poſito &amp; ſublato uno, ponitur &amp; tollitur alterum;</hi> Beſides, there is this grievous inconvenience it runs do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right into, that the Miniſter ſhall be bound to adminiſter the Ordinances (particularly the Sacrament) unto peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when they are bound upon pain of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170195:11"/>damnation not to take them. Upon this ariſes inextricable difficulties which as they encline men to ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo they leave the doubtfull Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in ſuch a caſe, that he can hardly ever act in faith upon ſuch foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>It is my opinion therefore, that the Covenant may be conſidered in the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial grace thereof and in ernal admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, and thus it belongs only to the elect and regenerate: Or in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral grace and external adminiſtration of the Ordinances, and thus it belongs to the whole Church as viſible, and to the ſeveral members alike, whether regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate or not.</p>
               <p>My reaſons for this latitude are theſe:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. It is manifeſt that the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Jewes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. were Gods peculiar people, in covenant with him, by the texts fore-quoted; and this is amply proved by Mr. <hi>Blake, Treat. Cov.</hi> p. 189, 190. but that moſt of them were only aequivocally ſo, is by others aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>gratis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. It is plain, that the Gentiles are ingrafted into the Olive of the Jews,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170195:11"/>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.24. that is, into their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal covenant, which covenant muſt be the covenant of grace, for elſe it could be no prejudice for any of them to be broken off, nor priviledge for any of us to be ingrafted in. And it muſt be as to the external adminiſtratiò, for elſe neither could any of them be broken off, not any of us ingrafted in.</item>
                  <item>3. It appears, that the Promiſe or covenant of Grace in the external ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration belongs to all that the Lord our God ſhall call, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. <hi>To thoſe that are afarr off,</hi> (that is, the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles) and their children, when the Lord ſhould call any of their parents, as it did for the preſent to the Jews, and theirs.</item>
                  <item>4. The called, no doubt, are many more than the elect; <hi>many are called, but few choſen.</hi> The called are ſuch, as Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> phraſes it, as are brought in covenant, The choſen, ſuch as are brought up to the terms of it. Now it is to be conſidered, The called contain the choſen. As there is an outward vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and an effectual vocation, yet that outward is real as well as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; So there is an outward being in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170195:12"/>covenant, and effectual, (as we ſpeak for diſtinctions ſake,) Yet that outward is real, not aequivocally only.</item>
                  <item>5. The Scripture puts a real diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the Nation of the Jews, as being in covenant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1. and 9.4. and others that were alienated from the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> without hope, without God in the world, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. but if none but the regenerate are in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, there is no ſuch difference ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally between a Jew and Gentile, Chriſtian and Heathen, but aequivocal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly onely, in which manner methinks the Scripture ſhould not be made to ſpeak ſo abundantly.</item>
                  <item>6. For this latitude, as to Obligation and priviledge of Ordinances, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10. <hi>This is my covenant ye ſhall keep between me and you, every man-child among you ſhall be circumciſed.</hi> Here I note, that the waiting on Gods ordinance, is the keeping the covenant it ſelf, in the external adminiſtration; And ſurely there is ſo much plain ſtrength in the inſtance of circumciſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>Jud.</hi> 5. from this large right of Ordinances from covenant-relation, that it alone will hold againſt all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170195:12"/>can be ſaid againſt it.</item>
                  <item>7. Excellent Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his <hi>Inf: Bap:</hi> p. 224. <hi>mihi Ed.</hi> 3. highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending Mr. <hi>Blakes</hi> opening of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional covenant, and affirming that he hath fully proved, that the reprobate (meaning of profeſſors) is within the verge of it, he adds, <hi>And doubtleſſe this imereſt in the covenant is afruit of Chriſts death.</hi> Now if it be ſo, how can it be aequivocal only? that is, an interect or priviledge, which will become a lie, and diſſimulation for thoſe that have it, to aſſume; and can that be a fruit of Chriſts death?</item>
                  <item>8. If no unregenerate Chriſtian be in covenant but aequivocally, then muſt not ſuch a one bring his child to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, nor partake himſelf of Chriſtian communion, but it is a meer mockery of Chriſt (as ſome ſeem to me here to ſpeak harſhly) to avoid which, he muſt tenounce his profeſſion, and never come to the Supper, and to the other Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, but only as an Heathen and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidel.</item>
                  <item>9. Then thoſe that are diſciples of Chriſt (for ſo was <hi>Judas</hi>) muſt not be caught to doe all things Chriſt hath
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170195:13"/>commanded, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20.</item>
                  <item>10. The Scripture (as Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) ſpeaks of dealing falſly in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, breaking, and not being ſtedfaſt in it: but if the regenerate only be in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, there can be no ſuch thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, but nominally only.</item>
                  <item>11. Chriſt ſaid expreſly to the twelve, Doe this, Drink you all of it, that was a command, and yet one of them was unregenerate; From whence it follows, that receiving the Sacrament is a duty of a diſciple, though unregenerate, and ſo the covenant, as to priviledge of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, belonging to ſuch. For my part, I cannot but think thoſe titles of Diſciples, Beleevers, Chriſtians, Saints by calling, and the like, given to all within the Church, are titles of right, and not nominal only. <hi>We muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh</hi> (ſaies Timſon) <hi>of beleeving in a large ſenſe, and of beleeving in a ſtrict ſenſe, both to be accounted true beleeving in Scripture ſenſe: The denomination of a beleever,</hi> (and ſo Saint, Chriſtian,) <hi>is as well derived from a right object beleeved on, as from the holineſs of the ſubject belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</hi> (Anſw. to Mr. <hi>Col:</hi> p. 153.) It is in my apprehenſion appoſitely ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</item>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170195:13"/>
                  <item>12. The covenant is founded upon grace. <hi>Gratia</hi> (ſaies <hi>Bullinger,</hi> Decad. 5. Ser: 6.) <hi>eſt favor numinis, quo Deus pater, nos propter Chriſtum complectitur, et donis inſtruct.</hi> Now in the Scripture there is two-fold grace; General grace, and Special grace; God is ſaid to love all, (that he would have all to be ſaved) yet elect ſome; Chriſt is ſaid to dye for all, and to dye for his ſheep; Both theſe are true, whatſoever men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, the Scripture muſt be beleeved, and we muſt not argue from the one to the deſtruction of the other. To define this ſenſe orthodoxly how both are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, who is ſo wiſe to undertake? One <hi>Cottier,</hi> a grave French-Proteſtant Divine, in an Epiſtle of his to one of their Provincial Aſſemblies, and well approved of by them, having ſtudied this point long, ſaies thus. <hi>Ad haec reſpondemus, non eſſe aſyſtata, quia gradu &amp; modo differunt. Deum putamus poſſe magìs et minùs velle. Par eſt majora ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gìs, minora minùs velle. Quod verò de Deo dicitur, Chriſto etiam convenit, Pro omnibus mortuus, magis vero pro Electis.</hi> Doctor <hi>Twiſſe</hi> ſaies thus often, <hi>Fatemur et nos Chriſtum-mortuum eſſe pro: omnibus
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170195:14"/>et ſingulis, hoc ſenſu, nempe ut inomnes &amp; ſingulos per mortem ejus redundet ſalus, modò in ipſum credant.</hi> Lib. 2. Crim. 4. Sect. 6. For my part, I dare not be pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory in determining this ſenſe of General grace, it ſuffices me that there is ſome ſenſe thereof according to the word of truth, and I ſhall only obſerve this one thing, that in the Scripture this General grace belonging to all in ſome Orthodox ſenſe whatſoever it be, is often appropriated to the viſible Church, who are ſaid to be <hi>redeemed,</hi> to be <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>ſanctified with his blood:</hi> in way of diſtinction from the world; when ſome of them are repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, and periſh with it, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Jo.</hi> 15.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. And herein I do conceive we may ſee how the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace in this latitude to the whole Church may ſtand upon a real, and not an aequivocal foundation; and that will be, if we doe not reckon the unregenerate and non-elect to be in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in reference to ſpecial grace, as Chriſt is ſaid to dye for his ſheep and elect, whereof theſe cannot partake in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, only in the account of men, which is nominally only; but in reference to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170195:14"/>General grace, as Chriſt is ſaid to dye for all (and that not nominally, aequivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, in the account of men only; but really, ſo that the tender and offer of Chriſt to all is ſerious and real) as it is appropriated to the Church that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives it, with diſtinction of priviledge from the heathen or world, that doe not receive this grace and Goſpel, but deny it. And this by the way I ſhall humbly offer, for the removing ſome grand objections which ſtick with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. For inſtance, <hi>The Sacraments are ſignes of grace, inſtituted to teſtifie the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and having the thing,</hi> ſaies. <hi>Gilleſpie,</hi> Aar: rod bloſ. B. 3. c. 13. Therefore they belong to the regenerate only. Again, <hi>It is not credible that Chriſt ſhould ſay, This is my body broken for you, and my blood ſhed for you, if</hi> Judas <hi>were amongſt the other diſciples.</hi> B. 3. c. 8. Again, <hi>The Sacrament is the communion of the body &amp; blood of Chriſt,</hi> with the like. I anſwer, The Sacraments are ſigns directly of this general Grace, as it is appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Scripture to the Church and they do teſtifie to every nember the being and their having thereof, by way of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage and diſtinction from the world;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170195:15"/>And thus, as it is credible that Chriſt ſhould ſay there are ſome branches in him that yet are fruitleſſe; that <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould ſay, ſome are bought by the Lord, that deny him; and <hi>Paul,</hi> that ſome are ſanctined by the blood of the covenant, that trample upon it, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the texts fore-quoted; So is it credibſe that Chriſt ſhould ſay theſe words, <hi>This is my body broken for you,</hi> to <hi>Judas</hi> among the reſt, and in the ſame ſenſe is there a communion of Chriſts body and blood to all within the Church, (even as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaies to all the people. <hi>Rehold the blood of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which the Lord hath made with you. Ex.</hi> 24.8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.19.20.) though ſome of them be profeſſors only. Two things here may be demanded, 1. How can this General grace of the covenant be appropriated to the Church, which belongs to all the world? I anſwer. It belongs to the world only in regard of publication, tender, and a kind of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tential intereſt if they come in; but it belongs to the Church by way of actual intereſt, as already come in (See my <hi>Rejoynd.</hi> p. 202.) ſo that one is ſaid to be in covenant, and the others yet ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170195:15"/>from it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12.2ly. What is that then which brings a man into this outward actual intereſt in the covenant, whereby this General grace thereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to him by way of priviledge now, when as yet he is no more partaker of the Special grace thereof than before? I anſwer with Mr. <hi>Hudſon,</hi> Vind. p. 8. There are two Sieves which God uſeth, the firſt is to ſift the world into a viſible eccleſiaſtical body; The ſecond is to ſift this viſible eccleſiaſtical body, into a ſpiritual inviſible body. The one Sieve is managed by the hands of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the other is in the hands of God only: Into the one a man is brought by the outward call of the Miniſter, and his own anſwering that call in recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the doctrine of Chriſt, and ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Ordinances; Into the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a man is brought only by election and regeneration.</item>
                  <item>13. Laſtly, The covenant under the New Teſtament is ſaid to be better than under the Old, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.22. &amp; 8.6. But to account this priviledge of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances which was in common to the Jews (as is proved before) to belong now only to the regenerate, is to make
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170195:16"/>it worſe under the New teſtament than under the Old, which is injurious to doe. <hi>Arbitrari</hi> (ſaies Calvin, Inſt. l. 4. c. 16. Sec. 6.) <hi>Chriſtum adventu ſno pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris gratiam immiouiſſe, aut decurtaſſe, execrabili blaſphemia non vacat.</hi> I know ſome do make this difference between the New and Old Teſtament, that the Jews were all called Gods people, and reckoned in covenant, though many of them were wicked; but it is not ſo now (ſay they) under the New. Againſt theſe I ſhall oppoſe only thoſe two plain texts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11, 12. there are ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous perſons enumerated, <hi>a Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, covetous, drunkard,</hi> yet <hi>within,</hi> (that is, within the Church and covenant) yet <hi>a brother.</hi> So 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.15. There is the diſorderly perſon, yet <hi>count him not as an enemy;</hi> that is happily (conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the word in other places, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.16.) count him not as one out of the Church, an Unbeleever or Heathen, <hi>but admoniſh him as a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> And indeed, unleſs ſuch be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked on as brethren, and as within, how can there be any excommunication, for <hi>what have we to doe to judge thoſe that are without?</hi> I know that <hi>Cameroes</hi> authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170195:16"/>is here quoted, but that grave and pious man Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> hath made it his buſineſſe to confute this difference, in the 27, 28, and 29 Chapters of his Treatiſe of the Covenant; wherein as I find Mr. <hi>Anthony Burgeſſe</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in this point commending that Tract as ſolid and judicious, in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of Juſtif: after he had ſeen what hath been put in againſt it; likewiſe Mr. <hi>Vines,</hi> and others; So doe I humbly judge his labours there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are worthy to be atteſted, as very ſerviceable to the Churches peace.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170195:17"/>
               <head>SECT. 3.</head>
               <p>VNto the Church, under that noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as his Church, or people, the Lord hath vouchſafed his ordinances by way of priviledge and diſtinction from the world. <hi>He ſhewed his word to Jacob, his ſtatutes and his judgements unto Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, he hath not done ſo to any nation, as for his judgements they have not known them,</hi> Pſ. 147.19, 20. Pſ. 78.5, 6, 7. <hi>What ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage then hath the Jew? Much every way, chiefly becauſe that unto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the oracles of God,</hi> Rom. 3.12. <hi>To them pertaineth the adoption, the convenants and the ſervice of God,</hi> Rom. 8.4. with Eph. 2.12. Upon this account, do our Divines ſolidly (as I think) make the Ordinances, the right adminiſtration of the Word and Sacraments (under which, a profeſſion of the doctrine of Chriſt, prayer, and other worſhip is comprehended) to be the notes or marks of the viſible Church. It is true indeed, that the Goſpel is to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched unto every creature to bring men
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170195:17"/>in unto the Church, as the Jewes no doubt might uſe the Word to make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes, nevertheleſſe the word of God as other ordinances, cannot be ſaid to pertain unto any out of the Church, in the ſenſe of the Scriptures now mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, until they receive the doctrine thereof, and externally ſubject them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſame. For this ſame pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of ordinances, or this donation of ordinances by way of priviledge to the Church, in diſtinction from others, is a thing to be ſtood upon as a matter very conſiderable, both becauſe, if we let this advantage fall, we ſhall preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly level a Chriſtian with an Heathen, the Church of Chriſt, with the Pagan world: and alſo becauſe the Lord hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theſe his ordinances (whereby the advantage of them does appear) to be the ordinary means of beſtowing his effectual grace, which he hath indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely promiſed in the uſe thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170195:18"/>
               <head>SECT. 4.</head>
               <p>VPon this latitude of the convenant, and this priviledge of ordinances belonging thus to the Church, as a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prium quarto modo,</hi> or an eſſential mark thereof, it muſt follow, that every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>in ſtatu quo,</hi> muſt have a right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>evol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on him, or flowing to him from that relation as a member. Only here wee muſt obſerve two diſtinctions.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. We muſt diſtinguiſh between a Right unto the effectual benefits of Chriſt held forth in an ordinance, as particularly the Lords Supper; and a Right to the external ordinance: The former right indeed, belongs to none but the regenerate; but the latter belongs to all within the Church, to all alike that are Members. <hi>Aliqui induunt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum</hi> (ſays <hi>Austin</hi>) <hi>uſque ad Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum receptionem, aln ad vitae ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem.</hi> I know ſome chuſe to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh here between an active <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ight in the Church to conferre the Seals, and a paſſive right in a viſible Member to receive; a right <hi>in foro Eccleſiae,</hi> and <hi>in foro Dei.</hi> But for my part, I think this former plain diſtinction of mine, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting an active and paſſive right <hi>in fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170195:18"/>Dei &amp; Eccleſiae</hi> alike, is rather (for theſe two reaſons, ſee <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.) to be uſed; and in other terms may, if you pleaſe, be expreſſed thus. The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may be conſidered either Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexly, with the entire fruits and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of the Covenant, unto which truth of Grace is neceſſarily required to the obtaining thereof: Or preciſely in the Ordinance it ſelf, and ſo it is Church-memberſhip alone, or external covenant-relation, denominating the ſubjects, Saints, Beleevers, Diſciples, Chriſtians, that gives men right unto the ſame. See reverend Dr. <hi>Worths</hi> Inf: Bap: p. 16. It is one thing what is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the receiver in his coming or that comes to the Sacrament (as of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and him that prays in their hearing and prayer) and another thing what is requir'd to receiving: ſo that elſe he muſt not come.</item>
                  <item>2. We muſt diſtinguiſh between a Right, and uſe of that right; Though this right unto all the ordinances be in common, It muſt be acknowledged for the uſe and actual partaking of ſome or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, particularly the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; there is a difference to be put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſuch as are not of age or capacity,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170195:19"/>but want the uſe of reaſon (as Infants, Idiots, Diſtracted, with the like) and other members; the direct and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate ground hereof lying herein, in that the uſe of a right, is not of ſo large ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, as the right is. A man may have a right to a thing, or to do a thing, when it is impoſſible for him to uſe the thing or to doe it, and the impoſſibility does diſoblige, and excuſe him from the doing. It is thus with infants and diſtracted perſons in point of the Lords Supper; it is not for want of a right they are not admitted, (any more than the infectious or ſick) they have a right, nay a full plenary right (let others uſe their own terms as they will) as appears con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly by the other Sacrament of baptiſme, where there being only a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive reception, which they are capable of, they do, and muſt receive it: But it is becauſe they cannot uſe the ſame right here, where ſuch an activity is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, as they are not capable of; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as in their eſtates they have a right to them, but they do not manage them. An heir in his infancy <hi>is Lord of all,</hi> in reſpect of the one, and yet <hi>differs not from a ſervant,</hi> in reſpect of the other, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.1.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170195:19"/>
               <head>SECT. 5.</head>
               <p>FRom this conceſſion of mine about Infants and the Diſtracted, it cannot be argued, <hi>à pari,</hi> by my oppoſers, for an excluſion of all ignorant, unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and ſcandalous perſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe in the one they ſtand wholly on the point of Right, but in the other we look only on the uſe of that tight. The unregenerate (ſay they) have no right to the Sacrament, and if they be viſibly ſo, through ignorance or ſcandal, they muſt be excluded: We ſay Infants and the diſtracted, have a right, but only they have not reaſon to manage their right, as the other have; ſo here is no parity. The truth is, it is memberſhip (as before) that alone gives right, ſo that though a perſon be unregenerate he may have a right to the ordinance, and whether he be Infant, Diſtracted, Ignorant or Scandalous, it is all one for that, if he be a member, this external right is the ſame in the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170195:20"/>one as in the other; Now the right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame, in the uſe of the right muſt lie all the difference; which between theſe is plain enough; the one have the exerciſe of reaſon, and are thereby able to act from a principle of reverence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, the other have not. The <hi>Corinths</hi> ſin of not diſcerning the Lords body, was more of careleſnes or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe, than bare ignorance; there is as much difference between Infants and Ignorants, (as I have ſaid other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where) as between a Doe not, and a Cannot, if the one does not, it is their fault; but the other cannot, and are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe there is yet a farther thing here, moſt conſiderable, and that is this. The very ground upon which we are to do any thing, or leave it undone, is the conſideration of duty; The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, as it is our rule, ſo it muſt be the reaſon of our actions. Now there is a difference in the very point of obligation or duty, between Infants and Diſtracted perſons, and Ignorant and Scandalous perſons. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Apoſtle is this, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. Let a man examine himſelf, and ſo let
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170195:20"/>him eat, diſcerning the Lords body; Now as for Infants, and the Diſtracted, they are not bound to this command, it is impoſſible for ſuch to examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and diſcern the Lords body; and there can be no obligation to that which is naturally impoſſible: But as for. Scandalous and Ignorant perſons, they are bound to examine themſelves, they are of capacitie, and are bound to get knowledge, and diſcern the Lords body, Who can deny that they are bound to do this, and that if they do it not, it is their ſinne? It is true, an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant perſon cannot examine himſelf, as well as a knowing Chriſtian; but he can examine himſelf though ſo farr that he is bound to it: He cannot hear and apply the Word, as a man of more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; but he can hear and apply the Word after a ſort, though as an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant man, which he is bound unto; and ſo far as he can apply the word, he can examine himſelf, the doing of one, is a doing of the other. Likewiſe, an unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate man cannot diſcern the Lords body with that faith and love as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate do; but yet nevertheleſſe, in point of dutie, the caſe is plain, every
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170195:21"/>man muſt doe ſtill what he can, that God may help him to do what he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. That which is a ſin to neglect or leave undone, is a dutie to be done; but it is a ſin in Ignorant and Scandalous perſons not to examine themſelves and diſcern the Lords body, and no fin in Infant and Diſtracted perſons; and therefore it is a dutie in the one, and not in the other. And if it be a dutie, here comes in then this rule, which can never be taken off, that Mans impoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in the manner of performance of a dutie, muſt not make void Gods autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in the ſubſtance; and ſo I cloze up this, if there be a dutie incumbent upon Ignorant and Scandalous members in reſpect of this Sacrament, which is not on Infants, and thoſe which have not the uſe of reaſon, then can there be no argument here from the non-admiſſion of the one, to the excluſion of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And this might ſuffice, but I will adde.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It cannot be reaſonably imagined that ſuch a ſtate of perſons (as Infants and Idiots) in the Church ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to actual receiving, that in the diſcretion of the Church are no proper
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170195:21"/>objects of Church-cenſures in point of offending, which growen perſons in the Church are, though never ſo ignorant. As <hi>John Timſon</hi> hath put in to my aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in his <hi>Bar removed, p.</hi> 6. I will add, it is as unreaſonable likewiſe that ſuch a ſtate of men in the Church as ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant perſons, ſhould not be capable of a right of receiving the Sacrament, who are upon their miſdemeanour lyable to a cenſure of exluſion from it. <hi>Eadem eſt ratio contrariorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The non-admiſſion of Infants, and Diſtracted or Idiots, is the office of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſingle Miniſter, belonging only to the right adminiſtring of the ordinance; ſo that the precept alone, Let a man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine himſelf, and diſcern the Lords bodies, does ſuffice for the doing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: But excluſion of ignorant and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous perſons is an act of Juriſdiction, and belonging (according to the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians) to the Elders: ſo that there are other texts required, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count whereof that is to be done, to wit, thoſe texts which concern diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Put away from among you ſuch a perſon.</hi> There is not therefore the ſame reaſon for the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170195:22"/>one, as for the other, as may be gather'd farther from what will follow. There is more required, and another ground, to an act which is eccleſiaſtically inflictive of puniſhment, than to a bare act of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral diſcretion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Ordinances all are to be uſed only for edification: Now the work of the Sacrament on the receiver being on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by way of ſign, as the underſtanding is exerciſed thereon, it is not poſsible, that thoſe who have not the uſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to diſcern any meaning here of can be edified, or have any real grace wrought on them by it. But for ſuch as are of years &amp; underſtanding, though ſpiritually ignorant and ſcandalous, though unregenerate (for the regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate may ſometimes be ſuch) I do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they are capable through the grace of God to receive good by it, as by the word; the Sacrament being nothing elſe but a viſible word, or an appendix to the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>As for the ignorant in the firſt place, I ſuppoſe ſuch as are of age and reaſon, let the Miniſter ſpeak of Mans miſerie, redemption by Chriſt, and tell the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple plainly the meaning of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170195:22"/>they come unto, in as few plain words as they can and ought, who can deny that they may not receive inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) and with inſtruction, convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) now at this time they are here, as at another? If they do not, the fault will be their Miniſters or their own. The Sacrament, <hi>mediante verbo,</hi> through the word, will be granted a teaching ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but the Word does accompany the Sacrament, and is indeed a part of it. The Novices of the Jews were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the meaning of the Paſſeover and ſome myſteries of their Religion; at their eating the Paſſeover (<hi>Godwin,</hi> Jewiſh Antiq. l. 3. c. 4.) the Paſchal Lamb was appointed for a teaching ſign, and memorial in their generations, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.26, 27. So doubtleſs is the Sacrament a teaching ſign alſo. I muſt confeſſe, if you will ſay that ſome are ſo groſly ignorant that they are not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable for the preſent to learn, or be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by publick teaching, then may you have the libertie for me to number them amongſt Idiots, and ſuch as have not the uſe of reaſon, and ſo deal with them accordingly; and if indeed there be ſuch, we had beſt happily, for avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170195:23"/>cavil, to diſtinguiſh between theſe (excepting them, together with Infants and the Diſtracted) and thoſe whom I ſpeak of, that though they be ignorant, are of diſcretion and capacitie to edifie by the publick ordinances; and as for ſuch, it ſeems to me againſt ſenſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that they may not receive inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and edification by the Word that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companies the Sacrament, (eſpecially in things of the Sacrament) as well as by that which goes before, or after it. And by the way, as for the younger ſort come out of their childhood, my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is with <hi>Aquinas, Quando pueri in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiunt aliqualem uſum rationis habere, ut poſſint devotionem hujus Sacramenti con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere, tunc poteſt eis hoc Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum conferri,</hi> Part 3. Quaeſt. 80. Art. 4.</p>
               <p>For the Scandalous in the next place, I would have ſome to know or conſider that the Sacrament is an ordinance wherein the curſe and wrath of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin is held forth in the ſufferings of Chriſt, as well as pardon upon repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Herein is <hi>the joynt ſtrength of the Law and Goſpel applyed in power to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and a moſt high-aggravating
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170195:23"/>of ſin upon the conſcience,</hi> ſaies Mr. <hi>Blake,</hi> in his late Book, called <hi>The Covenant ſealed,</hi> in reference to his former, <hi>The Covenant opened,</hi> ch. 7. Sect. 13. Arg. 3. &amp; 4. A ſin-aggravating, heart-brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſoul-humbling ordinance (as he calls it) is a means to reclaim even a ſcandalous ſinner.</p>
               <p>Reader, I ſpeak not theſe things on the one hand, to hinder Catechiſm, Examination, and any means of private conference for the bringing our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple unto knowledge; Nay, I am not againſt a prudential making uſe of this ſeaſon to this end; but only in regard that few Miniſters doe or can go to all their people, and their people will not come to them, I doe conceive it may be ſatisfactory to their ſpirits in doing their office, that though ſome perſons be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, yet coming to the Supper, and hearing the nature and uſe of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment laid open, there is hope through Gods grace, that they may receive at the very time competent information to be edified and wrought on by it. I will ſpeak plainly, they may receive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction for the knowing (according to their modell) <hi>the wretchedneſſe of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170195:24"/>ſin, that Christ is the Son of God, through whoſe name alone we can be ſaved, and that he is held forth as crucified in the elements, and tender'd to beleevers,</hi> which is as much as Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> ſaies, he dares re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire to admittance, <hi>Cov. Seal. p.</hi> 233. Again on the other hand, I ſpeak not neither to favour the ſcandalous, my doctrine is rather too harſh in the caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them out, yet am I not ſo far gone, as to think that it is not poſſible for ſuch a perſon (not yet under cenſure) to be wrought on, or edified by this ordinance. No, let but a right application of what is held forth herein be made by every receiver, according to the ſtate of his ſoul, and what can be more effectual through the word to break his heart? Let the man which is moſt keen againſt ſin, conſider what I have propoſed in my <hi>Rejoynder,</hi> p. 37, 39, 40, 75, 76. 112, 113.235, 236, 237, 238, 239, 255. and he will ſee this is no looſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine I have taught.</p>
               <p>Neither may they ſay this is no means to work grace or repentance, but confirm it; this is not an ordinance for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; but for edification<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For I ſay otherwiſe, It is a means of edification
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170195:24"/>and ſalvation, and therefore unto ſome likewiſe of converſion. <hi>The whole exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Chriſts officers in diſpenſing the word, ſeales, and all other ordinances of Christ,</hi> ſay the <hi>London</hi> Divines, (in their <hi>Jus Divin. Reg. Ec. p.</hi> 36.) <hi>is for the edifying the Church of Christ,</hi> or the viſible body, <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.11, 12. with <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5, 6. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11, 12. From hence then I argue, If the Lord hath appointed all his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances within the Church for the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the whole, and there be ſome unregenerate within the Church, then is the Sacrament appointed for ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate mens edification, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently their converſion, for otherwiſe ſuch cannot at all be edified unto ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But the former is true, therefore the latter. Again, The ſolemn applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the covenant to a mans ſelf, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his eſtate, to wit, of ſalvation through Chriſt, if he will beleeve and repent, and of judgement from Chriſt, if he continues in his ſinnes, and does not turn effectually to him, is the very onely way whereby the Spirit uſually worketh conviction and ſincere conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: But actual receiving of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a ſolemn means of ſuch an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170195:25"/>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> I pray ſee what I have written in the fore-quoted places for the clearing of this, and compare it with the ſubſtance of what Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> hath put in ſince (and, it may be, more cautiouſly expreſt) in the ſaid place of his <hi>Cov: Seal.</hi> p. 204. &amp; 240. which hath much confirm'd me; and I am perſwaded, when this matter is a litle more laid to heart, that many will not only be ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe with him, (ibid. p. 240.) that <hi>there is more weight herein, than perſonally hath been acknowledged;</hi> but alſo, that though it be objected againſt my do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that it ſtrengthens the hands of the wicked, <hi>Ez.</hi> 13.22. yet ſhall the godly find here a ſword put in their hands for the ſmiting the wicked, the ſecure, and hypocrite, up to the heart, with this Sacrament it ſelf; while they are but taught to apply what is held forth to them according to their condition.</p>
               <p>Indeed I conceive a forbearance ſometimes for all this may be piouſly adviſed upon the account of prudence, and the ſolemnitie of the ordinance, to doe more good by it; (which I ſhall ſpeak ſomething of in the end,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170195:25"/>to yield what may be, to the ſatisfying the pious) but this will not come up to a neceſſity. All the diſciples of Chriſt were ignorant in the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of Chriſts death and reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and <hi>Judas</hi> was ſcandalous (See my <hi>Rejoynd.</hi> page 15.) yet Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded neither of them at his Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170195:26"/>
               <head>SECT. 6.</head>
               <p>WEll now, let thus much be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that the Lord hath his Church in ſuch a latitude, to take into it whole Nations, regenerate and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate; That the priviledge of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances belongs to this Church by way of diſtinction of it from the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That every member thereof therefore hath a right unto the ordinances devol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on him from this Church-covenant-relation: While yet it is confeſſed, that there are ſome which through their incapacity of reaſon cannot uſe the ſame. The reſult of all will come to this, that there is no perſon of diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on within the Church can be debarred any publick ordinance, particularly the Sacrament, before he be turn'd out of the Church, with which, this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ordinances is convertible, and from it inſeparable. The Sacrament is the communion, or token of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in Jeſus Chriſt; But every
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170195:26"/>Church-member in <hi>ſtatu quo,</hi> is in Chriſt, <hi>Jo.</hi> 15.2. and in ſome ſenſe partaker of his blood, ſo as to ſanctifie him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10 29. and redeem him, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. and therefore his right is good to that which is in the ſame ſenſe the token hereof; So long as he is in communion, how can he be debarr'd the communion? while he is in the body, he may partake of the body; The Church is the body of Chriſt, and ſo long as we are one body, we are one bread, and partakers of that one bread.</p>
               <p>I muſt yet follow moreover, if it cannot be proved that Jeſus Chriſt hath given order for the caſting out ſome from the Church, ſo far that for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent they are thereby cut off their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal covenant-Church-relation, we muſt maintain a promiſcuous communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the largeſt way, as learned <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus,</hi> and others before <hi>Eraſtus</hi> have done; which yet I dare in no wiſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, ſo far as it oppoſes an Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal government diſtinct from the Civil within the Church. It is my opinion therefore, that the Lord Jeſus hath ſet up a power of the Keyes under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, diſtinct from the Magiſtrate, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170195:27"/>he hath taken order, that if there be any perſons within the Church that are ſcandalous, and remain obſtinate after due admonition, that they are to be caſt out by the cenſure of Excommunication, which being ſuch as turns them out from the Church (<hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 5.7, 13. <hi>Io.</hi> 9.22.3. <hi>Io.</hi> 10.) their right unto the ordinances muſt needs fall together with their Church-relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and then they are juſtly to be kept from the Sacrament. So that I herein declare againſt an <hi>Eraſtian</hi> in-diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary promiſcuous communion, though I ſtand for an orthodox diſciplinary Free-admiſſion.</p>
               <p>And here I will advance this one ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> which will ſtand, I ſuppoſe, when others will not; and it is this. If the Scripture does al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low an excluſion of ſome from the Church in general, or from her ſocietie and communion in general, then may ſome be excluded from the Sacrament, becauſe the Sacrament is a part of that communion. But the Scripture does allow and command this, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Purge out the old leven; Keep no company; Put away jrom among you ſuch
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170195:27"/>a perſon; Let him be to thee as, an heathen.</hi> Therefore an excluſion from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon thoſe grounds as do reſpect it onely as a part of Church-ſociety in general, is to be maintained againſt the <hi>Eraſtian</hi> by excommunication; as an excluſion upon other grounds, as parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly from the diſtinct nature of the ordinance is to be oppoſed againſt others that would have it without excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170195:28"/>
               <head>SECT. 7:</head>
               <p>FOr the Excommunicate, there is a received diſtinction of ſuch that are ſo, Either <hi>Ipſo jure,</hi> or <hi>De facto;</hi> Thoſe are accounted <hi>ipſo jure</hi> excommunicate, whoſe ſcandal and impenitency is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the Church, that there need no tryal for their conviction. Thoſe are <hi>de facto</hi> excommunicate who have farther a legal ſentence paſſed on them. It muſt bee acknowledged that many Divines and Churches of God have allowed the Miniſter a liberty to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Sacrament from perſons Excommunicate <hi>ipſo jure,</hi> before ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; unto whoſe reverend authority, I have ever judg'd with due limitation much is to be ſubmitted; ſo that upon their ſcore I have expreſt my ſelf in my <hi>Rejoynd.</hi> p. 21, 26. ſo farre, that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing there are ſcandals, 1. Notorious, that they offend the Congregation. 2. Open, that they need no proof or debate. 3. Actual, or in the preſent
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170195:28"/>fact, that no repentance can be plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it may not matter much, if you deal with ſuch as excommunicate, when you judge it like to doe good. In extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary caſes, ſome extraordinary procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings break no ſquares. Nevertheleſſe (ordinarily) upon my fartheſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, I do believe it a thing more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the ſcope of the Scripture, and leſſe lyable to oppoſition, to reſolve that an eccleſiaſtical judgement firſt paſſe upon a perſon, before he be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded any part of our Churches publick communion: and therefore I doe own here that thing (as fit and good) which is noted by Mr. <hi>Collings, Vind. Suſpenſ: &amp; Presb:</hi> p. 36. That though I grant to the Miniſter thus much <hi>upon a pinch,</hi> in caſe of ſome intollerable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, yet as to what is ordinarily to be done, <hi>all my arguments</hi> are ſo framed, as to <hi>conclude,</hi> that a perſon muſt not be only <hi>de jure,</hi> but alſo <hi>de facto</hi> excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, before he be debarred his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
               <p>My reaſons are, 1 Becauſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle commanding the <hi>Corinths,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Not to keep company nor eat</hi> with thoſe brethren, that were <hi>fornicators, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170195:29"/>railers,</hi> and the like, layes down expreſsly this proceeding, <hi>For doe not ye judge thoſe that are within? v.</hi> 12. that is, this not keeping company is intended no otherwiſe, than upon a judgement foregoing. <hi>This refuſing to eat with ſuch a one, was by vertue of a judicial ſentence</hi> (ſaies Gilleſpie, <hi>Aar. rod. bloſſ.</hi> p. 430.) <hi>paſt againſt the ſcandalous perſon.</hi> And <hi>Beza, De Presb.</hi> p. 57. So in 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.14. <hi>If any obey not, note that man, and have no company with him.</hi> The diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſon is firſt to be noted, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, according to our chief Anti-<hi>Erastian</hi> Divines, <hi>Beza, Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, Rutherford, Gilleſpy.</hi> Set a mark upon him, or a cenſure, and then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from him. Indeed it is a queſtion whether this <hi>Note</hi> or <hi>Judging,</hi> in theſe texts be authoritative, or private only; I muſt confeſs if they be not authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, but of private diſcretion, as <hi>Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> holds, then this will not reach the purpoſe, nor this <hi>Have no company,</hi> I ſuppoſe then, reach to the Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe it ſeems not reaſonable, that a penalty ſhould be inflicted on a perſon before a judgement be given. I will expreſſe this in the words of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170195:29"/>
                  <hi>Bowles,</hi> quoted by another out of his Evangelical Paſtor. <hi>Qui omnium peſſimi, uſque dum eccleſia ſuâ ſententiâ decretoriâ pro canibus et porcis habendos declaraverit, non mihi cum illis ut canibus &amp; porcis agendum eſt. Latronem, qui mortem commeruit, nullus jure de vitâ tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> dum judex et reum declaraverit et ſententiam tulerit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe there are like to follow many flippery and dangerous inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences upon the allowing the Miniſter power of doing otherwiſe: inſomuch as I find <hi>Beza</hi> in his book againſt <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> very often, and very earneſtly me-thinks, ſpeaking to this purpoſe. <hi>Etiamſi ſuis oculis minister quempiam viderit aliquid agentem, quod coenae excluſionem mereatur, jure tamen nec debeat nec poſſit, niſi voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, convictum, legitimè deni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſecundum conſtitutum in eccleſia ordinem, damnatum, à menſa domini, cum authoritate prohibere.</hi> See p. 26. 23. 75, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe Excluſion from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according to my judgement, is not to be allowed by any means upon thoſe reaſons which are moſt ſtood upon from the nature of the ordinance it ſelf, as diſtinct herein from others, but upon
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170195:30"/>the account of diſcipline only. <hi>To ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from the Lords Supper</hi> (ſaies Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtical Mr. <hi>Jeanes</hi> as the ſubject of his diſcourſe upon this queſtion, which he hath ſtrongly carried) <hi>is a kind of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical puniſhment, and therefore preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth an Eccleſiaſtical cenſure; though men have deſerved ſuch a puniſhment, yet it is not to be inflicted on them, untill they be legally cenſured,</hi> p. 118. Ed. 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170195:30"/>
               <head>SECT. 8.</head>
               <p>THat my mind here may be clearly underſtood, the controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween mee and thoſe that oppoſe me be more fully ſtated, and ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice avoided, I muſt crave pardon to uſe ſome more words, it may be ſome more than enough, upon this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</p>
               <p>In my Vindication of Free-admiſſion (my firſt little book, <hi>p.</hi> 33.) for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining my conceptions, I have laid down a diſtinction between diſcipline and worſhip. The exerciſe of the keys, as acts of diſcipline, I would have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted one thing, and the uſe of the ordinances, as acts of worſhip, to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Diſcipline to be in one element, Worſhip in another. I know, if ſome liſt to be contentious, they may confound theſe, but <hi>docendi gratiâ</hi> at leaſt, for the expreſſing my ſelf, no equitable man can deny me thus to diſtinguiſh for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Now there are two extreames,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170195:31"/>I conceive, concerning Free-admiſſion to the Lords Supper; On the one hand, of ſuch who are too large for it, and the other of ſuch as are too ſtrict againſt it.</p>
               <p>There are ſome then, as hath been touched before, that plead for free admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, not only in regard of Worſhip, but alſo in regard of Diſcipline; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming all excluſion from any of the publick Ordinances of God by the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Church, and indeed denying all Eccleſiaſtical government, diſtinct fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the civil, where the Magiſtrate is Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. There are others that plead a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt free admiſſion, not only in point of Diſcipline, but alſo in point of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, herein advancing the Sacrament above all other Ordinances, that thoſe who have a granted right to all other parts of Gods worſhip and Church-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion as baptiſed members, are deni-to have any right unto the Sacrament, though they be yet under Church-indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and not cenſured. The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (ſay they) requires truth of grace in the receivers; unleſſe a man be rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate on his own part, he is forbidden to come, and conſequently, unleſſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170195:31"/>trial and examination there be ſome evidence that he is viſibly or probably ſuch, on the Churches part, he muſt not be admitted. In the middle, between theſe extreames, my opinion (and the truth, as I think, without engaging o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) does lie; Affirming againſt the former, who are the <hi>Eraſtians,</hi> that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, hath ſet up a power of the keys in the Church, (as I have ſaid before) and that the Scripture is manifeſt for an excluſion of ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (to wit, the ſcandalous and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate) from Chriſtian communion in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and ſo conſequently from the Lords Supper, as a part thereof. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe I doe aſſert likewiſe againſt the latter, that there is no Scripture for the excluſion of any from this Sacrament without diſcipline, but that admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring and receiving the Lords Supper, is as free and univerſal (in the nature thereof to our members) as other parts of Church-communion.</p>
               <p>The ſame qualifications are required to effectual prayer, and other parts of Gods worſhip, as to the Sacrament; and as the want hereof puts no barre to the one, no more does it to the other. It
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170195:32"/>ſhall never be proved, I believe, that the Scripture hath advanced this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the Sacrament and other ordinances, that herein alone it muſt be better to omit the matter and manner both, than to do the matter, if it be not done in ſuch manner as it ought, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to all other duty. In ſhort then, neither the <hi>Eraſtian,</hi> nor ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid Suſpenſioner muſt have their wills; In point of Diſcipline, Free-admiſſion is to be denied againſt the one; In point of worſhip, Free-admiſſion is to bee maintained againſt the other.</p>
               <p>It is a thing very conſiderable in the holding any point, upon what grounds it is we hold it; Thoſe that oppoſe me in my opinion, are very hot for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion from the Sacrament, and I for my own part doe allow and uphold the ſame. An excluſion it ſelf, neither of us do deny, the very difference between us is, upon what grounds or arguments we hold it. Now all thoſe arguments for this excluſion againſt Free-admiſſion may be reduced to theſe two heads; Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſuch as do ariſe from the nature of the Sacrament, as diſtinct herein from all other parts of Church-communion;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170195:32"/>Or to ſuch as do ariſe from the nature of diſcipline, that reſpects the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Church in general, and ſo this Sacrament in common with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts thereof.</p>
               <p>Arguments of the latter ſort are thoſe, and thoſe only which are from ſuch texts. <hi>Let him be to thee as an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. Keep no company with ſuch. Pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge out the old leven. Avoid, withdraw from them. Put away from your ſelves ſuch a perſon;</hi> with the like. The ſumm where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of comes to this briefly. The Scripture commands Excommunication, that is, an excluſion from the Church, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety in general; therefore from the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament alſo. Theſe arguments now, I conceive, are firm; Free-admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as <hi>Eraſtus</hi> holds it, I maintain not.</p>
               <p>Arguments of the former ſort, are ſuch as theſe. The Sacrament is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed only for the regenerate. It is a ſeal of Faith, and ſet to a blank, if given to any others. Every one elſe does but neceſſarily eat and drink damnation in the Apoſtles ſenſe, with the like. Now theſe arguments, I conceive, are to be ſatisfied, &amp; taken off as ſuch as are both
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170195:33"/>invalid, and doe hurt. Free-admiſſion will ſtand for all them. Alas! were all ſuch arguments concluſive and true, what will become of the poor doubtfull Chriſtian? How ſhall he act in faith? How ſhall the Miniſter himſelf act? What will become of the Churches u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and peace, the command of Chriſt, and the foundation of diſcipline? If it be from the nature of the Sacrament, and theſe grounds, upon which men are to be excluded, then muſt they be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded if there were no diſcipline; then muſt the keeping away of ſuch not be an act of vindicative but diſtributive Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. As a godly Father ſhuts his ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born ſon from prayers in his family, and from his preſence: So does the Church (as I conceive) exclude her refractory children. It is not becauſe the coming to prayer is not the duty of ſuch a child, and is not a means to do him good; No; but becauſe indeed it is ſo, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would make him ſenſible hereby how highly he hath offended him, and how much the more hainous is his evil, to reclaim him. A man hath enjoyed thoſe priviledges and means of grace which ſhould have done him good, ſo
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170195:33"/>long, and he grows but the worſe: Well now, the Church in her excluſion, does as it were ſay thus to him, I will teach you Friend (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20.) to make better uſe hereof when I again admit you to them. If the Sacrament were not a mans priviledge before, and for his benefit, then could not (as I ſay) Suſpenſion be a judicial proceeding; It were not a puniſhment, but a delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; That cannot be in way of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is onely to preſerve a perſon from that which is noxious, and can be no wayes any good to him. It is not upon ſuch grounds therefore wee muſt ſtand; the Scripture knows no ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement (whatſoever humane pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence may make) of this Ordinance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove her fellowes in point of duty; but for ought I know, leaves every man free in the uſe of this, as well as all other of his outward priviledges, untill he bee legally deprived of the ſame by a juridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal cenſure,</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe (farther) It is a queſtion, Whether the debarring of perſons from the Sacrament, be an act <hi>ſpecialis muneris,</hi> of the power of order, belonging to the Miniſter ſingly; or of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170195:34"/>the power of Juriſdiction, not belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him alone, but in common with others, that are rulers in the Church The School-men (as Mr. <hi>Jeanes</hi> tells us p. 95.) are of the former opinion, who affirm, that <hi>this denegation of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment if not to be conſidered as a judicial action, or inflictive of puniſhment, but only as a prudent and faithfull adminiſtring of the ordinance;</hi> (<hi>Suarez.</hi> in part. 3. <hi>Thom.</hi> Tom. 3. Diſp. 67. Sect. 3. p. 856.) and ſo belonging to every private Miniſter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, by vertue of his office. Now let this be well conſidered, and if any of the arguments of the former ſort (laſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) be binding, that is, if it can be proved that the nature of the Sacrament be ſuch, that thoſe who have a full right, and are in actual poſſeſſion of all other parts of Church-communion, have yet no right hereunto, and upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count are to keep, and be kept away from it, then muſt theſe School-men in all reaſon be in the right, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negation thereof to ſuch, be requiſite to the faithfull adminiſtring the ordinance, which is the office no doubt of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Miniſter; But the reverend Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, generally diſliking that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170195:34"/>ſuch a power ſhould be left to every ſingle Miniſter, wiſely conſidering the dangerous conſequents thereof alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, that this ſame excl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> from the Sacrament, does belong to the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Juriſdiction, and conſequently, if they will be conſonant to themſelves, they ſhould deny that any of thoſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which ariſe from the nature of the ordinances alone, as diſtinct from others, are cogent, and ſtand upon thoſe only that ariſe from diſcipline.</p>
               <p>As for the Schoolmen, by the way, it wil be no wonder if they ſtand u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe arguments from the nature of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as herein tranſcending all other ordinances, whoſe ſuperſtitious conceit of Chriſts corporal preſence in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, could not chuſe but induce them to it; as may appear upon their ſolutions of ſuch queſtions as theſe, <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum peccator ſumens corpus Chriſti Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentalitèr peccet? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>idetur quod non; Quia, Sicut hoc Sacramentum ſemitur guſtu &amp; tactu, ita &amp; viſu; At peccator non peccat videndo. Reſpondeo, Quòd per viſum non accipitur ipſum corpus Chriſti, ſed ſolum Sacramentum ejus. Sed ille qui manducat, non ſolum ſumit ſpecies Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentales,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170195:35"/>ſed etiam ipſum Chriſtum qui eſt ſub eis. Aquinas</hi> Part 3. Quaeſt. 80. Art. 4. Upon ſuch anſwers as theſe, I am the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>e moved with their thoughts about this matter; as alſo with ſome paſſages often quoted out of ſome of the Fathers. Of whom I doe obſerve, that thoſe out of whoſe writings the Papiſts uſually have moſt for them, are moſt harſh, and high flowen in their expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about keeping of ſinners from the Sacrament, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> (a man of a hot ſpirit, according to his life, <hi>Soc:</hi> Hiſt. Eccl. l. 6. c. 14 &amp; 16.) and thoſe, whoſe writings are quoted as moſt clear on our ſide, (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) are more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and open in their ſpeeches about admiſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:170195:35"/>
               <head>SECT. 9.</head>
               <p>THeſe things laid down, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the controverſy between me and others, about Free-admiſſion, will amount to theſe two queſtions.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Whether there be any argument from the nature of the Sacrament, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcipline, that remains binding ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scripture, for the neceſſary excluſion of ſuch from the ſame, who are yet rightly impriviledg'd, and actually poſſeſſed of all other parts of Church-communion, being baptized intelligent members. I put in the word Neceſſary, becauſe prudentially by way of adviſe, ſomething may be granted and wiſhed.</item>
                  <item>2. Whether there be any ſuch juri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical proceeding or cenſure in diſcipline to be proved, either expreſly, or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence from Scripture, as Suſpenſion, diſtinct from Excommunication.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:170195:36"/>
               <head>SECT. 10.</head>
               <p>FOr the former of theſe queſtions, It ſeems to me, (as is before ſaid) that were the Presbyterian judgement right and uniform to its ſelf, I ſhould not need to have any diſpute with them; for, if Suſpenſion, or excluſion from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be no other than a juridical acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which thoſe that are for Ruling El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders do, and ought to maintain, then can no argument from the diſtinct na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this ordinance, that would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this excluſion, though there were no diſcipline, be of ſufficient force for it. It there be one ſuch, then is this excluſion thereby proved to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Miniſters office in his faithfull adminiſtration of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance (as before) and not to the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of juriſdiction. Nevertheleſſe, for ought I ſee, when they come to diſpute, it is theſe arguments mainly they ſtand upon. And therefore, for my own part, upon conſideration of thoſe perplexities which ariſe from hence on tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170195:36"/>together with the injury that is hereby offered to the Church in lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ground of all her diviſions and ſeparations (and upon no other intereſt of parties I profe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e in the world) I have thought good to do my endeavour for the anſwering and taking off thoſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, in what I have formerly writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and I hope I have in ſome meaſure done it, eſpecially in my <hi>Rejoynder,</hi> to ſome mens ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>For 1. let but a candid interpretation, be given on that Chapter, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no more ſtreſſe on the words, than the purport of the contents will bear, and ſo thoſe objections that ariſe from thence be allayed, which ſink deepeſt; For which, I humbly offer that 4th Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in my <hi>Rejoynder,</hi> p. 29. to 44.2. Let the covenant be layed down in that latitude as the Scripture does, and ſo thoſe objections from the Sacrament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſeal, be ſatisfied, ſeeing the ſeal <hi>(Quoad jus)</hi> muſt be as large as the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; For which read p. 170. to 180. 3. Let the Sacrament with all the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances be look'd upon, as inſtituted for the viſible Church, which conſiſts of the unregenerate as well as the regenerate,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170195:37"/>and conſequently, that it is both the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and a means (ſubordinate to the word) for edification of the one as well as the other; whereby that obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that the Sacrament is for confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and not converſion, is taken off, For, though this ordinance is no conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ordinance to the Heathen, it hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders not, but it may beget grace in a Chriſtian. And I muſt confeſſe, I ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wonder, to ſee how this ſticks upon the ſpirits of moſt at their firſt thoughts: The Sacrament is no ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance (ſay they) for the Heathen to convert them; therefore it is no means of converſion: whereas indeed the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is no ordinance for the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, not becauſe it is not converting, but becauſe God hath appointed it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for his Church. The Sacrament is no confirming ordinance to the Heathen; therefore is it no confirming ordinance? There is the ſame arguing in both: It is neither a converting nor confirming or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance to the Heathen, becauſe it is no ordinance at all for them. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, That it is a means for edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church, (as I ſay, and chuſe to lay it down ſo) whether her Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170195:37"/>bee regenerate or not, I humbly tender my <hi>Rejoynder,</hi> p. 206. to 241. and likewiſe what learned Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> hath put in more lately, <hi>Cov. Seal.</hi> chap. 7. ſect. 13 and 14. who doth fully agree with me in this point, and hath eaſily anſwered Mr. <hi>Gilleſpyes</hi> twenty argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which have been ſtood upon ſo much by many.</p>
               <p>Let theſe three things, now I ſay, be done, as I think they are, and there will be nothing left, as I ſuppoſe, that can hold conſiderable againſt the negative of the former queſtion; for which, it ſhall ſuffice me to produce the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my reverend and pious, though harſh adverſarie, Doctor <hi>Drake</hi> himſelf. <hi>Let Mr.</hi> Humfrey (ſaies he, p. 116.) <hi>prove that actual receiving is a debt on the part of a natural man, and we ſhall be farr enough of hindring any the payment of their debts.</hi> Now this is proved in the third particular; The Sacrament is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the Church, the Church conſiſts of unregenerate, as well as others, which is a firm and ſolid probation; and is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that ſtrong bottom (as Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> acknowledges it, <hi>Cov. Seal.</hi> p. 247. whatſoever others have ſaid hereof) on
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170195:38"/>which not only my book, but both his too, ſo far as concerns this matter, are founded.</p>
               <p>And as for that inſtance of <hi>Judas</hi> joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by me to the precept, <hi>Doe this. Drink ye all of it. And they all drank of it.</hi> (in the choice of that text, <hi>Mark</hi> 14.23.) it does adde much ſtrength here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, let it be taken directly, not on the part of the admitters, as it is uſually urged, but on the part of the receivers; Thus. That theſe words <hi>Do this, Drink ye all of it,</hi> was ſpoken to All preſent, it will be granted. That <hi>Judas</hi> was preſent, the Evangeliſts do as it were command, at leaſt allow us to beleeve, while they tell us he ſate down with the reſt, and his hand was at table. Now ſuppoſing him preſent, Chriſt bids <hi>Judas</hi> expreſly to receive, (to <hi>Take</hi>) amongſt the reſt; From whence, actual receiving is irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragably proved the duty of a diſciple, though unregenerate, or in his natural eſtate. And then you ſee what Mr. <hi>Drake</hi> yields me, and what would bee wonne, though he ſhould not; for this foundation, as to the main, muſt hold ſo long as the precepts of God can be preſerved from being made void by
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170195:38"/>mans tradition. <hi>Go and diſciple all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> ſaies Chriſt, <hi>baptizing them, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you,</hi> Mat. 28.19, 20. From hence we collect, that thoſe who are diſcipled by baptiſm, that is, are baptized members, muſt be taught to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all the commands of Chriſt. But the Sacrament is one of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</p>
               <p>I will onely urge here farther one argument, which I muſt confeſſe, ſinks deep into me, as that which is not mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fetcht from the brain, but from the hearts of many that are wounded by it. That doctrine which cuts off every doubtfull Chriſtian from the Sacrament, is harſh doctrine and not to be endured: (By the Doubtfull Chriſtian, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand a man in doubt of his regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a man that is indeed truly gracious, but doubts ſo, that he is inclined rather to think he is not.) But this doctrine that holds it not the duty, but unlawful for every unregenerate man to receive, does cut off every doubtfull Chriſtian from receiving; Therefore this doctrine is not to be endured. The Major I hope will not be denied, the Minor I prove,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170195:39"/>That doctrine which concludes it to be ſinne in the doubtfull Chriſtian to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament, cuts off the doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſtian from receiving. This is manifeſt. But this doctrine concludes it to be ſinne in the doubtful Chriſtian to receive. <hi>Probo.</hi> That which a man is not fully perſwaded in his conſcience is lawfull to be done, it is ſinne if it be done: This is the very direct meaning of thoſe words, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is not of faith is ſin.</hi> But if it be not the duty, or it be not lawful, according to this doctrine, for any man which is not regenerate, to receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then cannot the doubtfull Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, that is in doubt whether he be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate or not, be fully perſwaded in his conſcience, that it is his duty, or that it is lawfull for him to receive; and conſequently, if he receives, he ſinnes. <hi>If he eateth and doubteth, he is damn'd if he eat.</hi> This I humbly conceive is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing. The argument I preſume is ſtrong as it is urged by others on the part of the admitters. If truth of grace be neceſſarily required to receiving, how ſhall the Miniſter act in faith, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be aſſured of the truth of grace in an
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170195:39"/>other? But as I doe urge it thus, on the part of the doubtful receiver himſelf, I think it is irrefragable. And as it is that, which hath wrought much with me in my <hi>Rejoynd.</hi> p. 30, 31. So hath it with pious <hi>Timſon,</hi> who agrees with me in it, <hi>Anſ. to Mr. Col.</hi> p. 51. and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Mr. <hi>Blake, Cov. Seal.</hi> p. 192. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you may ſee a ſympathy of our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoules and ſpirits in this point. I ſhall not need therefore to ſay any more of this former queſtion, but refer to what is already written.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:170195:40"/>
               <head>SECT. 11.</head>
               <p>FOr the later queſtion; Were the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer granted, that Excluſion from the Sacrament, does indeed belong only to the power of juriſdiction, which the Presbyterians grant; and conſequently that no arguments from the nature of this ordinance barely, as diſtinct from all others, without diſcipline are firm and cogent for it; which they ſhould grant likewiſe. Then will the whole diſpute between me and them, come to this iſſue, that they muſt prove, Either, that there is a power in the Miniſters to ſet up a diſcipline, or a part of diſcipline which is not preſcribed in the Scripture, a thing which none of them I think will maintain: Or that there is ſuch a part of diſcipline preſcribed, in Scripture, as excluſion from the Sacrament, diſtinct from excluſion from the Church; that is, Suſpenſion, defined to be, a juridical act of the Officers of the Church; whereby upon their having had due cognizance
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170195:40"/>of ſuch, as are unworthy the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, they deny the Ordinance to them, as a cenſure, diſtinct from, and in order to Excommunication.</p>
               <p>And here, that the whole difference between me and the moderate Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian (unleſſe where they fall from their own principles) does indeed come to this only, I ſhall produce one teſtimony that may ſuffice. Reverend <hi>Beza, De Presb: &amp; Excom. p.</hi> 23. layes down, or yields to us theſe three things.
<list>
                     <item>1. That the Supper is inſtituted for diſciples.</item>
                     <item>2. That all ſuch as profeſs Chriſt, though hypocrites, are diſciples. <hi>Quales fateor quidem generaliter omnes cenſeri, qui ſe tales eſſe teſtentur, etiamſi reipſâ nihil mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nùs ſunt quam Chriſtiani.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. That they are ſo to be accounted of, in regard of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, untill they are orderly convict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſentenc'd.</item>
                  </list>
                  <hi>Deinde pro non detectis haberi, qui tales eſſe non fuerint, eo, quem Deus in eccleſiâ conſtituit ordine, convicti, &amp; pro rebellibus damnati.</hi> So pag. 27. <hi>Chriſtus, inquit D.</hi> Eraſtus, <hi>juſſit omnes edere illum panem, et ex poculo illo bibere; Ergo neminem vult excludi qui ſe ſuum diſcipulum profiteatur. Id verò concedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, adeò quidem ut ipſos etiam hypocritas,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170195:41"/>quamdiu vel penitus ſunt tecti, vel neque authoritate publico convicti, et damnati in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſcipulos numeremus.</hi> I know ſome of our Divines of late, but not of the gravity and moderation of <hi>Beza</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> p. 41. <hi>Gilleſpy,</hi> Mr. <hi>D.</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) are more bold with the command of Chriſt, and taking up <hi>Beza</hi> for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thus much, do reſtrain it to the regenerate only. But this reverend man, who is much rather to be heard, durſt not do ſo, but is plain you ſee and clear in theſe conceſſions,, upon which, the ſubſtance of my whole opinion (at leaſt, as to the Miniſters part) will ſtand. For if the Sacrament be inſtituted for diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; and all that profeſſe Chriſt are to be accounted ſuch; and none of them to be excluded, until they be <hi>convicted and condemned for rebels in that order God hath appointed,</hi> (as he affirms) then muſt that diſciplinary Free-admiſſion which hold before excommunication, be good, unleſs it can be provd that there is ſome other cenſure in the order God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, whereby the ſaid rebels are to be condemned, beſides excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which I deny. And ſo you ſee to what a little point our difference draws.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170195:41"/>
                  <hi>Beza</hi> ſayes, they muſt be convict and ſentenced firſt, before they be excluded, as well as I; only he conceives there is a leſſer cenſure to be firſt inflicted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the greater; which I muſt confeſſe I find not. And herein likewiſe <hi>Beza</hi> himſelf acknowledges thus far, that there is ſeldome mention in the Scripture of any ſuch leſſer cenſure, but the greater only. <hi>Tantum abest ut major excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatio cenſeri poſſit praeter Dei verbum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vecta, ut contra rara ſint in ipſo verbo Dei expreſſa minoris excommunicationis exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla; majoris autem multa, p.</hi> 11. Now if here inſtead of <hi>rara,</hi> he had ſaid <hi>nulla,</hi> I think he had delivered the very truth.</p>
               <p>My reaſons againſt the affirmative of this queſtion, are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Lord Jeſus in that primitive inſtitution under the Goſpel, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15, 16, 17. hath preſcribed no other parts or order in diſcipline, than admonition and excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. After the offending partie is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed privately, then publiquely, If he will not hear the Church, (ſayes Chriſt) let him be as an Heathen, that is, let him be excommunicate, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170195:42"/>to thoſe that oppoſe <hi>Erastus.</hi> Now if the Apoſtles have preſcribed any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther order of diſcipline, than what is preſcribed in this original pattern, let it be produced; If not, then may this text be ſufficient, that there is no ſuch mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle thing in the order Chriſt hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, as Suſpenſion, between admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and excommunication.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the power of the Keyes are given for binding and looſing, which I conceive is done, not in regard of a perſons being debarr'd or admitted any ordinance; The Levitically unclean were kept from the ordinances during their uncleanneſſe, yet were not their ſins bound thereby; for many times they might become unclean without ſin, <hi>Lev.</hi> 21.3. <hi>Numb.</hi> 19.8. But in regard of that ſtate and relation men have to the Church outwardly, and Chriſt, as vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible members, from which, while they are excluded, their ſins are accordingly, and no otherwiſe bound or retained (becauſe there is no remiſſion out of the Church, or out of Chriſt, the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble herein, <hi>clave non errante,</hi> preſenting the inviſible) as they are looſed by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing received, in again through repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170195:42"/>From whence I argue, where the ſins of men are not bound or retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there is no Church-cenſure, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19. <hi>Io.</hi> 20.23. But it is not exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding men from the Sacrament, but the excluding them from the Church, and ſo Relatively from all its benefits, in that ſenſe as we ſay, <hi>Extra quam, non eſt ſalus aut remiſſio,</hi> that does bind the ſins of men upon earth. Therefore ſuſpenſion can be no Church-cenſure diſtinct from excommunication. See my <hi>Rejoynd.</hi> p. 145, 150. As the being within the Church puts men into a ſtate, whereby every member, Relatively, though a Reprobate, is ſaid in Scripture to be in Chriſt, redeemed, ſanctified, to have communion of his body and bloud, with the like; ſo does the caſting them out of the Church put them likewiſe into a contrary ſtate or condition, whereby they are Relatively to be ſaid without Chriſt, without God in the world, without redemption, remiſſion, ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe the Scriptures whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they ſpeak of excluſion in point of diſcipline, doe ſtill ſpeak in general. <hi>Purge out the old leven. Have no compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170195:43"/>Put away from among your ſelves ſuch a perſon, &amp;c.</hi> From whence my argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will be framed thus. If there bee no place in Scripture to prove any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion at all, but ſuch as ſpeaks of exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the Church, the whole lump, ſociety in general, or the like; then is it not poſſible to prove by the Scripture Sacramental excluſion, as diſtinct from Church-excluſion. Or, If there be no other <hi>medium</hi> in Scripture-diſcipline (I ſpeak of the word Diſcipline all the way reſtrainedly, as to this part of cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) but excommunication it ſelf, for the proving a withholding any at all for moral uncleanneſs from any publick or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance (as may appear by any thing of weight in <hi>Gilleſpyes</hi> 14 Arguments for excluſion from the Paſſeover. B. 1. c. 12.) then cannot ſuſpenſion be proved, as diſtinct from, but only as conjunct with excommunication. The conſequence here is apparent; But the former is true, therefore the latter. In a word, the Scripture knows no other excluſion that is diſciplinary, but a caſting out of the Church, and ſo from the Sacrament only, as included in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170195:43"/>
               <head>SECT. 12:</head>
               <p>ANd this I take to be ſo true, full, and convincing, that I ſhould hardly need any thing more for the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering even the whole of thoſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for juridical ſuſpenſion, which is of late put forth by Mr. <hi>Coll:</hi> in that book of his upon this ſubject, wherein I may truly ſay there is beſtowed a good deal of reading, only as it were to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver how little there is to be found in others, and nothing from himſelf (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides humane authority) for his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>I muſt confeſſe there are here Certain Scriptures and Reaſons urged by him, with ſo much pedantry, that is more than enough; and it will be neceſſary that I give my thoughts concerning the Scriptures, though for what is mere for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malitie, oſtentation, or perſonal abuſe, it may paſſe. I pray God teach that author, and all of us, to become a little more vile in our own eys, that we
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170195:44"/>may learn to vilifie others leſſe. The Scriptures are four or five.</p>
               <p>The firſt is <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6. <hi>Give not that which is holy unto the dogs, nor caſt ye your pearls before Swine, leſt they trample them under their feet, and rent you.</hi> For my judgement on this text, I conceive,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That this ſpeech was proverbial a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Jews; and I think I have read or heard it is in the <hi>Talmud.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. That the purport or meaning, not the letter, is to be attended.</item>
                  <item>3. That this meaning or ſenſe hereof tends unto prudence, or a prudential managing of ſuch things as are deſigned to a good end.</item>
                  <item>4. That theſe holy things and pearls, (though they may more ſpecially in the coherence, and in the thing, agree with admonition) are to be taken in general for all ſuch things as have a ſubſerviency to holy uſes. 1. Becauſe the text li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits them not. And 2. Becauſe there is no neceſſitie for us to do it.</item>
                  <item>5. That theſe doggs and ſwine are not to be taken in general for all ſorts of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for the ſame reaſons on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.
<list>
                        <item>1. Becauſe the text it ſelf does deſcribe them, to wit, to be ſuch as will
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170195:44"/>trample the holy things under their feet, and turn again and rent us.</item>
                        <item>2. Becauſe there is likewiſe neceſſity ſo to do. For no holy thing or pearl can be given to dogs or ſwine by this precept, it being boldneſſe to limit what Chriſt hath not limited.</item>
                     </list>
But ſome holy things (as the word, or admonition) may be given, and was given by Chriſt himſelf unto ſuch as are dogs and ſwine in general in other texts, as ſuppoſe ignorant and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous perſons; therefore muſt not the ſenſe of theſe dogs and Swine, be of all ignorant and ſcandalous ſinners in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; but on neceſſity be confined to the text in hand, in which ſenſe it is true, that no holy thing at all is to be given to ſuch.</item>
                  <item>6. By theſe holy things then and pearls, I underſtand all things, whether matters of Religion, which are more properly the holy things, (as wholeſom counſels in Scripture, pious conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, opening our experiences, and in general, the ordinances;) or matters of morality, which may be more properly the pearls (as precious ſayings, wiſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious contrivances, advice, actions) ſo far as they are either appointed of God,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170195:45"/>or made uſe of by reaſon for the Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of others. And by dogs and ſwine I underſtand all perſons, whether igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or not ignorant, ſcandalous or not ſcandalous otherwiſe, that are but like in the uſe hereof towards them, to tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple on) he things, and rear the givers, that is both to contemn the one, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite the other.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The ſubſtance then of this precept or counſel of Chriſt, as I am fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, without binding others, comes to this, that every man in the managing of good things, ſhould be prudent, ſo far, as to have a care, and ſuch regard to the perſons (with other circumſtances) to whom he diſpenſes them, that we are to forbear, when we ſhall but exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, give occaſion of contempt, and do no good by them.</p>
               <p>For inſtance, ſuppoſe a man (otherwiſe godly) is in a paſſion, ſo that I ſee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, (which is a pearl and good thing in its ſeaſon) would be ſurely contemn'd, if I ſhould give it him at the preſent, and make him flie upon me, in this caſe now, under this dogged humour, this rule of Chriſt commands me in prudence to forbear, and take another opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to do my duty.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:170195:45"/>
               <p>This foundation being laid, I ſhall here propoſe theſe two queſtions.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. How can our delivering the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to our intelligent &amp; unexcommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate members, be a giving thereof un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to dogs, ſeeing we are ſure they will not turn again upon us, and rent us for that; Or ſwine (which ſome diſtinguiſh) ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they doe not trample thereupon, by neglect, vilipending, deſpiſing or reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of it (for that is trampling the holy things in the text) but ſo far as we can poſſibly ſee, do reverently receive it?</item>
                  <item>2. Whereas if we with old the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from them, unleſſe we could have a fair proceeding unto cenſure, which would ſtop their mouths, they on the contrary will turn upon us and rent us; withall trampling thereupon, by not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at all for it: Whether or no is not this rather a plain breach (in the want of prudence) of this rule, ſeeing ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them is ſuppoſed to be a holy thing and pearl, and theſe perſons in this caſe, unleſſe we could take farther or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, we are ſure are doggs and ſwine in reference thereunto, in the very ſence of the text. Let thoſe tender Miniſters that have been ſo much ſcrupled about
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170195:46"/>this buſineſſe, lay this conſideration well to their hearts, together with the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and ſweetneſſe of their Saviour, whoſe commands are not grievous, and they may happily find ſatisfaction, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in this very text, from which they may have likely received at firſt the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt impreſſions towards the enſnaring of their conſciences.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The ſecond Scripture is 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.21. <hi>Ye cannot drink the cup of the Lord and the cup of Devils, ye cannot be partakers of the Lords table, and the table of Devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the ſenſe of theſe words, I judge there is no difficultie. Many of the <hi>Corinths</hi> being brought over from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm to Chriſtianity, and ſo members of that Church, made nevertheleſſe but little conſcience (as if it were a lawfull thing) of going to the temple of Idols, &amp; eating there, of thoſe things that were ſacrificed to Devils; Now to reclaime them from this, and prove that they ought not ſo to doe, the Apoſtle uſes this argument; I <hi>ſpeak to you,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>as wiſe,</hi> that is, as rational men, <hi>Judge ye what I ſay; Doe not you know that the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170195:46"/>Sacrament which we celebrate is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the body &amp; bloud of Jeſus Chriſt, ſo that all that partake thereof are viſibly profeſſors of communion with him? So all that partake of thoſe meats ſacrificed to Idols, are viſible profeſſors of communion with theſe Devils. Now there is no agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between Chriſt and theſe Idols, ſuch things are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, you cannot partake of the table of Lord, and the table of Devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which words wee are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by this Cannot, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal cannot, that is, in reaſon you cannot; this is manifeſt, becauſe he lays it down by way of argument, which the more you conſider, will be the leſſe denied; and by theſe words, <hi>the cup and table of the Lord, and the cup and table of Devils,</hi> we muſt underſtand the outward ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in both, that is, the bread and wine in the Sacrament, and that meat offered to Devils in their Idol-temple, the reaſon being open, becauſe the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle argues from their partaking of the one, againſt their partaking of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>For thoſe Commentators (as <hi>Pareus</hi>) that reſtrain the ſenſe to inward ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170195:47"/>communion, becauſe we <hi>Can</hi> (ſay they) partake of the outward things in both, they go but on a ſlight foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for this <hi>Cannot,</hi> we ſay, is not a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural cannot, but a logical cannot, A cannot argumentative. Ye cannot par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of this Sacrament (ſaies the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) and of thoſe meats ſacrificed to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, becauſe there is no agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe things (he explains his own cannot) there is a plain inconſiſtency in reaſon between them; for by the one we profeſſe communion with Chriſt, by the other with devils; <hi>and I would not have you</hi> (ſaies he, <hi>v.</hi> 20.) <hi>have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this purpoſe, that Note from <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi> upon the word cup is pertinent, that it is not ſaid, you cannot partake of the body and blood of Chriſt, which would rather expreſſe this inward communion, but you cannot partake of the cup and table, which muſt intend the outward elements, and not the things ſignified only, the very drift, reaſon, and matter of the Apoſtle elſe is evacuated. Not as Mr. <hi>Col.</hi> urges, <hi>becauſe Pauls argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is plainly to prove the unlawfulnes of their comming to this table, while they were
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170195:47"/>guilty of ſuch ſinnes,</hi> which is indeed a plain untruth, but becauſe his argument is from their partaking of the Lords ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as their duty, being Chriſtians, to diſprove their partaking of the meats offer'd to Idols with the Heathens.</p>
               <p>I know ſome interpret this Cannot morally, <hi>Id poſſumus ſolùm quod jure poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumus, You cannot,</hi> that is, in few words, you ought not; which might be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if they will apply it right, to wit, thus; You cannot, that is, you ought not, to goe to the Idol-temples, who are according to your profeſſion to bee partakers of the Lords table. But for them to apply it quite contrary, you go to the temple of Idols, and ſo you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, that is, you ought not, come to the Sacrament; This I muſt tell them cannot be admitted, <hi>Cannot,</hi> in the ſenſe of the Texts cannot, that is, cannot in any reaſon.</p>
               <p>Let this cannot then here be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, not of a phyſical cannot, nor a bare moral cannot, but a logical can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, grounded if you will on a moral cannot on the one ſide, yet ſo long as you ſhall not be able to deny the moral Can, which the whole former part of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170195:48"/>the chapter enforces, on the other, here will be nothing at all for the adverſarie. The Apoſtle does not ſay any where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, You partake of the table of Idols, or have eaten of thoſe meats, &amp; I would not have you have felloſhip with Chriſt; But he ſays plainly, you partake of the Lords Table, you are in communion with Chriſt, <hi>and I would not that ye ſhould have fellowſhip with devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus then the main being clear, I ſhall propoſe here four things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Whether it can be denied that this action of theſe <hi>Corinths,</hi> in partaking of theſe Idol-tables, was ſcandalous? <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalum</hi> being <hi>dictum vel factum minùs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum praebens atteri occaſionem rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. If it cannot, how then can any man gather an argument from this place (whatſoever they may do from others) for the keeping away perſons from the Sacrament for ſcandal, when the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle himſelf pleads the general privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theſe perſons comming to the Sacrament, as an argument to reclaim them from their ſcandall?</item>
                  <item>3. Whether this argument here may not be irrefragably advanced; Thoſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170195:48"/>that were by the A oſtles reaſoning en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged from partaking of the table of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, partook of the Lords Supper (for this is the ground upon which he proves they might not partake thereof) But not only thoſe <hi>Corinths</hi> that were more pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but thoſe ſcandalous patricularly, were hereby engaged, and warned from partaking of thoſe tables of devils; <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> theſe <hi>Corinths,</hi> though ſcandalous, were admitted to the Sacrament. Thus much is not to be gain aid <hi>they were.</hi> I adde, and <hi>they ought to be</hi> (tid excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate) upon the ſame conſideration, becauſe elſe you make a ſinfull <hi>medium</hi> in the Apoſtles Argument.</item>
                  <item>4. Whether many of our godly breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren that take occaſion from theſe words, to ſeparate from us in our mixt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, are not a little miſtaken in them, ſeeing the Apoſtle here pleads not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the comming of divers perſons (good and bad) to the ſame table, but againſt the ſame perſons, going to diverſe tables.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The third Scripture is, 1 Cor. 5.8. <hi>Therefore let us keep the feaſt not with the old leaven, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170195:49"/>
               <p>For the meaning of theſe words, we find in the beginning of the chapter, the Apoſtle is ſpeaking to theſe <hi>Corinths</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their gathering together in an ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical way, for the exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municating the inceſtuous perſon, as appears eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially from the laſt verſe, unto which with <hi>v.</hi> 7. and the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>v.</hi> 5. what <hi>Eraſtus</hi> oppoſes I judge is ſtrain'd and inſufficient, though what he urges upon the words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, were plauſible otherwiſe. For this now St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives his plain reaſon, which yet he expreſſes metaphorically, <hi>Know ye not that a little leaven, leaveneth the whole lump?</hi> that is, one ſuch evil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample tolerated, will bring a blot or infamy upon the whole Church, beſides the hurt it may doe through imitation. <hi>Purge out therefore the old leaven that you may be a new lump,</hi> that is, Caſt our of your ſociety therefore this perſon; <hi>For Chriſt our paſſeover is ſacrificed for us,</hi> that is, as to the ſenſe and matter agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.14. Chriſt gave himſelf for us to redeem us from all iniquity, and to be a peculiar people zealous of good works: ſo that Chriſt being ſacrificed for us, is an argument to us, as to purge
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170195:49"/>out ſin in our ſelves, ſo to purge out the old leaven from the Church. The word Old, happily may ſignifie, not every freſh ſinner for one lapſe, or ſo, but the veterate, and obſtinate therein. For the manner of the expreſſion, it is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought in by way of elegancy, in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of the Metaphor, as likewiſe the text that follows, <hi>therefore let us keep the feaſt.</hi> The words are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Igitur epulemur,</hi> as the olo tranſlation; that is, <hi>Ita<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſolennitèr vivamus;</hi> or, <hi>vitam preſentem tranſeamus;</hi> Let us live feſtivally: or as the Margin of our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Bibles, moſt properly, <hi>Let us keep holy day,</hi> to wit, in our communion toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as Chriſtians. Let us lead or paſſe our life, which ought to be a perpetual celebration of our redemption, <hi>Not with the old leaven, or the leven of malice or wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, but with the unleavened bread of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and truth;</hi> that is, what the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> did typically for 7 days, let us per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form in the truth and thing ſignified, all the days of our lives, to wit, purging out the leven both of imbred corruption, and ſcandal from amongſt us. So that to make here a ſolemn enquiry what is this feaſt we are to keep in the text, ſeems
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170195:50"/>to me, an injudicious and needleſs trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the ſubſtantive Feaſt being not in the text, but the Metaphor expreſt only in one verb <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> manifeſtly bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed to follow the alluſion, or to ſuit with the reſt in the ſenſe I have ſpoken according to <hi>Athanaſius, Chryſoſtome, Theophilact, Lyra, Calvin, Beza, 'Diodate,</hi> our Aſſemblies annotations, with the moſt upon the place. From all which, it will appear, that though this text may be well urged, as it is by <hi>Beza</hi> and his followers againſt <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> to prove Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, yet here is nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, to prove Suſpenſion as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from Excommunication: which Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> acknowledges in his <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of Ch: Gov:</hi> p. 349. <hi>We con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>that the debarring of men from any one Ordinance, was ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by the putting away of the leaven, but the putting a wicked perſon out of the church</hi> 1 Cor. 2. <hi>with</hi> v. 5, 6, 7, 13.</p>
               <p>The Fourth Scripture is 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. which with the words before is this, <hi>I wrote to you in an epiſtle not to company with fornicators; yet not altogether with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicators of this world, for then must ye needs
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170195:50"/>goe out of the world. But now I have wrote to you not to keep company, If any man that is called a brother, be a fornicator, or cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, or an idolater, or a railer, or a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, with ſuch a one no not to eat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this text there is only one difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to our purpoſe, and that is, what is meant by this Company and Eating? Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> in his <hi>Power of the Keyes,</hi> is ſomething willing to take it of ſacred communion only, as others both of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred &amp; civil upon the cenſure of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication; Unto which, as I have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver confeſt my ſelf inclining, ſo am I now no leſſe than ever. Notwithſtanding there are theſe reaſons may be produced for the contrary, that it is to be taken only of common eating and ordinary fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity, without cenſure.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Becauſe the Apoſtle ſeems to bring in this as a new matter from that before (which is more manifeſtly about ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication) though ſuitable to it. <hi>I wrote to you in an epiſtle, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Such as is the communion with theſe we are to avoid, ſuch is the eating, becauſe the one explains the extent of the other; But that ſeems to be of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170195:51"/>familiarity, <hi>Keep not company with them.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. That company and eating is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in this place to an heathen for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicator, which is not to ſuch a one cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a brother; But Sacramental eating or communion was not permitted to an Heathen; therefore it is not Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental eating, of which the place ſpeaks.</item>
                  <item>4. The manner of expreſſion, which is, by way of explanation, as to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, how farre this not keeping com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany reaches; <hi>with ſuch keep no company, no not to eat,</hi> as it ſhews this eating to be of the ſame kind with companying, ſo it ſeems plainly to hold it forth, as a thing the moſt common, or dinary, and the leaſt matter amongſt them to be admitted to, of any, <hi>No not to eat.</hi> But my oppoſers will hardly ſure conceive thus of this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and ſolemn eating at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If they will, (it being of old in common with their love-feaſts, and and mingled with them) why ſhould they ſcruple at free-admiſſion as to this ordinance, above other parts of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an communion, from which they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude none before excommunication?</item>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170195:51"/>
                  <item>5. There may be clear reaſon for a man to eat at the ordinance with ſuch a perſon, whom yet he is to avoid in his common familiarity, becauſe the one is neceſſary, which he is bound to obſerve as part of the ſervice of God; but the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (at leaſt as to the nature of the thing in its ſelf) is arbitrary, at his own liberty.</item>
                  <item>6. This may be exemplified in the Phariſees, who would not eat at their common table with any of the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, whom yet they could not debarre the Sacrifices, Paſſeover, or ſervice of the temple, many of them being not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Jews; but devout men.</item>
                  <item>7. There may very probably be a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between this <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in <hi>v.</hi> 11. and an <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in <hi>v.</hi> 13. &amp; 2. It may be one thing to withdraw our ſelves from ſuch a man, and another to remove ſuch a man from amongſt us. The one may reſpect Church-cenſure, and not the other.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Upon theſe reaſons I confeſſe for my own part, before I read <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> (which to ſay the truth I had not done, nor yet ſeen him, till after my <hi>Rejoynder</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad) I have been ſwayed to this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170195:52"/>But ſince I have read him and ſome of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> oppoſers, I am more indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oward the other.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Becauſe the moſt Commentators I ſee, and the ableſt of <hi>Eraſtus</hi> antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, do go that way, making theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as the reſt of the Chapter, ſerve for excommunication, and I have no mind to approve of the taking away of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſure, which this text as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, may help to maintain.</item>
                  <item>2. Becauſe the Apoſtle ſpeaks of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping company in general, and eating in general, and I begin to fear a man may be too bold to limit it to common fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity onely, as to ſacred only; Yet as to the limitations of that old verſe, <hi>Utile, lex, humile, res ignorata, neceſſe.</hi> I count theſe words in <hi>v.</hi> 10. will bear them out by way of proportion, to wit, Yet not altogether, for then muſt you needs goe out of the world.</item>
                  <item>3. Becauſe theſe reaſons I have laid down doe indeed ſeem to me cogent (at leaſt ſome of them) for the proving that common ſociety and eating muſt be underſtood here incluſively; but I think them not ſo cogent to prove it exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively, that ſacred communion and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170195:52"/>eating may not be meant here alſo.</item>
                  <item>4. Becauſe I queſtion whether a man be bound to avoid every ſcandalous ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in civil communion, or ordinary eating, unle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e in caſe of partaking in their ſins, by acting with them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance or the like, until he is cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Church, and ſo this precept may be perhaps to be underſtood only upon ſuppoſition, that there is a prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent eccleſiaſtical judging, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him to be avoided; for it ſeems a grievous thing to think, I may not eat with a covetous perſon, or the like, in our neighbouring invitations; yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I may be bound not to chuſe ſuch for my Companions in intimate familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</item>
               </list>
               <p>However, as unbyaſſed herein, and not more peremptory than the matter will afford; It ſhall ſuffice me to ſpeak to the text ſo far as it concerns my ſelf; To do which partially we muſt have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the following verſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>For what have I to do to judge them alſo that are without, doe not ye judge them that are within?</hi> The Illative, <hi>for,</hi> plainly brings the matter before to be concerned here, and the meaning of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170195:53"/>the words I take to be this; The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle may be ſaid to judge ſuch by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing rules, or giving precepts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning avoiding them, and the Church may be ſaid to judge them by doing an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to his preſcriptions; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that muſt be neceſſarily underſtood in their Elders meeting together accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Order for the excluding ſuch by eccleſiaſtical cenſure; Or the people only every one avoiding ſuch by a judgement of private diſcretion, I cannot deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; but rather doubt, whether any reaſons can be ſo manifeſtly laid down on the one ſide, but that there will be reaſon leſt like wiſe for the other.</p>
               <p>If this judging then, <hi>Doe not ye judge thoſe that are within?</hi> be meant of ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical cenſure, upon which, ſuch men are to be avoided, then muſt this cenſure be the cenſure of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For, That cenſure by which men are excluded Chriſtian Societie in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and not the Sacrament only, is the cenſure of excommunication. But ſuch is this, in the expreſſe words, Keep not company with ſuch. It is not ſaid on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Eat not with ſuch, but Keep not company, no not to eat, explaining as I
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170195:53"/>have ſaid, the extent thereof; And then you may have ſtill a text here, if you will, againſt <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> to prove excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication; but here is nothing againſt me to prove Suſpenſion as diſtinct from Excommunication.</p>
               <p>If by judging <hi>(Do not ye judge, &amp;c.)</hi> be meant only a judgment of private diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and no Church-cenſure, then muſt this keeping company and eating, be meant only of common familiarity, and thoſe reaſons before mentioned will certainly evince it upon that ſuppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; For it is a moſt grievous and unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing, that one private brother ſhould avoid another in any one of the publick Ordinances or worſhip of God upon his own private judgement. <hi>Privato cujuſquam ar bitrio hunc vel illum defugiendum relinquere nihil aliud eſt qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſchiſmatibus &amp; infinitis offendiculis janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am aperire,</hi> ſaies <hi>Beza De Presb.</hi> p. 91. and ſo <hi>Gilleſpie,</hi> and others; and then this text makes nothing for Suſpenſion nor Excommunication neither.</p>
               <p>There is but one thing here, which all have, can be urged: and that is this, If wee muſt avoid ſuch a perſon at our own table in common familiarity, then
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170195:54"/>much more at the Lords table. But this objection is ſufficiently met with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in the laying down my matter. It is true, if this avoiding ſuch, be upon a Church-cenſure (which then I ſay is excommunication, not ſuſpenſion) the argument, <hi>à minori ad majus,</hi> may hold. That cenſure, that excludes a man from commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eating, does much more exclude him from the Lords table; if from commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> familiarity, then much more from ſacred communion. But if this avoiding ſuch (which is ſuppoſed in the pleading here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) be upon private diſcretion, the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is no waies valid, becauſe the denyal of common eating at our own table is in every mans private hands, but the denial of eating at the Sacrament is in the Churches hands, and for one private brother to take upon him to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void another at the publick ordinance, before Church-cenſure, will not I hope be maintained, by any that are not in love with Schiſm and ſeparation.</p>
               <p>Unto this text I might adde a fifth, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.14. which is a parallel to it. <hi>If any man obey not our word by this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, Note that man, and have no compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170195:54"/>with him, that he may be aſhamed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here we have the ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and I conceive the ſame difficulty. For ſome do look on this <hi>Note</hi> here as pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, civil, common only; and ſome do take it to be Eccleſianical, authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, a Note of cenſure, for which <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, Ambroſe, Chryſoſtom, Theophylact, Theoderet,</hi> are quoted among the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the learned Anti-<hi>Eraſtians</hi> of late, do all go this way.</p>
               <p>For my part therefore (without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining that which is dubious, and having no need to determine it) I ſhould anſwer to this text as to the laſt. If this Noting be private onely, then does the Apoſtle command us onely not to keep common company or familiarity with diſorderly perſons, and ſo the text concerns not the Sacrament at all. If this <hi>Note</hi> be Eccleſiaſtical, then does the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle command us to excommunicate ſuch perſons, and ſo the texts concerns the Sacrament as a part of company in general, and no otherwiſe, which is moſt plain and undeniable, in that there is not a tittle in the chapter to point out to us this Sacrament in particular.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170195:55"/>
               <p>For the former interpretation there may be theſe reaſons, 1. The perſons to be noted are the diſorderly in the verſes before, that went about idle, and would not work for their living; Now the bare denying ſuch perſons entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their houſes, and not keeping them company, ſeems a direct and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient courſe alone to reclaim them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and ſet them to work, eſpecially when they knew the Apoſtles precept, That <hi>if any would not labour, neither ſhould he eat, v.</hi> 10.2. Theſe words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> may refer to the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and be thus conſtrued, <hi>Hunc no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum facite per epistolam,</hi> ſignifie that man by an epiſtle, to wit, that he may be cenſured if the caſe require, and not to be underſtood as already under cenſure. 3. The perſon that is under cenſure, is to be accounted as an Heathen, <hi>Matt.</hi> 18.17. but this perſon here is <hi>not to be accounted as an Heathen,</hi> (for ſo the word Enemy probably ſignifies, as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.16.) <hi>but admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a brother,</hi> v. 15.</p>
               <p>For the other interpretation there may be theſe reaſon.
<list>
                     <item>1. The perſon to be noted, is not only diſorderly, <hi>v.</hi> 11
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170195:55"/>but ſeems here alſo to be refractory; <hi>If any man obey nor,</hi> or will not obey.</item>
                     <item>2. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> is judged more than a bare <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> indeed ſignifies barely <hi>indico,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>notam impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. The <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> (which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire may be moſt obſerved) <hi>Keep not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie</hi> (as in the text before) is general, and indefinite, comprehending all ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, both ſacred and civil, and there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to limit the ſame in the text. Now to avoid a perſon ſo far, as to have no company in general with him, is not to be ſuppoſed, but upon an eccleſiaſtical cenſure.</item>
                     <item>4. The end wherefore the perſon is <hi>Noted,</hi> is the ſame with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, to wit, that the man be brought to ſhame or repentance.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>I muſt confeſſe, to deal ingenuouſly, If I were to chuſe out an argument to prove Suſpenſion, I ſhould pick out this text chiefly, which yet Mr. <hi>Coll:</hi> fore-quoted, hath not produced for one amongſt theſe others. And I would urge it thus, Here is a Noting of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to this end, that he may be aſhamed, which is probably a Church-cenſure. But this cenſure is not excommunication, becauſe the excommunicate is to be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170195:56"/>counted as an heathen, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. but this perſon is ſtill to be accounted as a brother, <hi>v.</hi> 15. (which reaſon is not the leaſt amongſt the reſt now mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) therefore muſt this cenſure be an Excluſion from the Sacrament only, or Suſpenſion. And this argument, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, were more to the point, than any of thoſe I read in this reverend Brother, which generally doe labour ſtill in this one fault, that they prove Suſpenſion by Excommunication, when they ſhould prove the ſame as diſtinct from it.</p>
               <p>Yet were not this argument neither to be thought ſufficient and convincing,
<list>
                     <item>1. Becauſe the ground on which it ſtands, is at moſt but probable; We are not ſure this Noting here is eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical.</item>
                     <item>2. Becauſe thoſe Divines that do underſtand this text, as well as <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. of Excommunication, do reconcile them both pretty well together.</item>
                  </list>
Some ſay the Excommunicate is not as a man quite diſmember'd, but as a diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed member under cure. It is not ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Some ſay he is caſt out, <hi>quoad us in ſe,</hi> not <hi>quoad jus ad rem.</hi> Others ſay he is indeed caſt hereby out of the Church,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170195:56"/>but this is conditionally, he is not as an heathen abſolutely, but that ſuch an expreſſion may be uſed. I will adde, A man may be Relatively put into the ſtate of a heathen, through ſome miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanour, when yet Really he may be a Saint and a true child of God. 3. If this does not ſatisfie, but that you think here is a cenſure, and that not ſo high as excommunication, it will not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low for all this, that it muſt be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily this ſuſpenſion, becauſe it may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing elſe as well, unleſſe there was ſomething in the place, to diſcover that the Apoſtle had ſome aim here in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular at the Sacrament; which being a vain thing to affirm, if you ſhould frame twenty kinds of keeping not company, or excluſions, as well as from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſhould ſay the Text means one of them, you would have quite as much from the place to prove the one as well as the other.</p>
               <p>To conclude then theſe Scriptures, (about which I have been ſomething long) Mr. <hi>Col.</hi> argues thus ſtill in the main (and in particular p. 87.) <hi>It is the duty of Church Officers to keep the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Church pure, for to this end is
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170195:57"/>the rod of Diſcipline put into their hands, Therefore muſt ſuch and ſuch perſons be excluded the Sacrament.</hi> But he ſhould ſay therefore they ſhould be excluded Church-fellowſhip; for to plead for ſuſpenſion from this Ordinance only, inſtead of caſting them out of fellowſhip in general, to this end that it may be kept pure, is nothing elſe but to yeeld openly, that Church-fellowſhip in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of it ſhould remain polluted and impure. And then will all theſe texts return moſt forcibly on himſelf, and overwhelme him. Chriſt does not ſay, keep the Sacrament only from Dogs and ſwine, but give no holy things at all to them. <hi>Paul</hi> does not ſay, Purge out the leaven from this ordinance only, but from the lump. He does not ſay, Keep not company only in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but Keep no company, Put ſuch a one from amongſt you; Let him be as an Heathen. The ſumme then is this, according to what hath been before. If theſe very Scriptures which are alleadged for ſuſpenſion, do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the Sacrament no otherwiſe but as a part of Church-communion, that is, if they doe not prove a man
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170195:57"/>is to be excluded from communion in the Sacrament at all, but only that they prove he is to be excluded commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in general, we ſhall not need any ſtronger proof againſt Suſpenſion, then that there is not ſuch a cenſure in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, as diſtinct from Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170195:58"/>
               <head>SECT. 13.</head>
               <p>THere are ſome other Divines of ſomething more candid ſpirits, that look upon Suſpenſion only as a pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, paſtoral duty, and no juridical cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſo labour to maintain it. For ſuch as theſe, I muſt acknowledge that thoſe reaſons of mine laid down before, do not ſtrictly meddle with them. It may ſuffice me as for ſuch, that they have <hi>Beza</hi> with the Presbyterians directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and no Scripture for any Suſpenſion at all (I ſpeak as to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament) whereon to build ſuch an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. And as for that they have to ſay for it, for that is the whole, that the Apoſtle commands a man to examine himſelf, and diſcern the Lords body, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which, we granting that infants and diſtracted perſons are not to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Miniſter; therefore ſay they likewiſe, neither ignorant nor ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous perſons, I conceive it too inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent a ground alone, to build a buſineſſe
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170195:58"/>of ſo much practical weight and trouble upon. I will adde therefore two or three reaſons more againſt this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A regenerate perſon that can exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelf, and diſcern the Lords bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the ſtricteſt ſenſe, yet may be ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, and for that ſcandal deſerve ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, as <hi>Theodoſius</hi> by <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> It is not therefore becauſe the Apoſtle commands a man to examine himſelf, and diſcern the Lords body, that a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous perſon is excluded; but, becauſe the Apoſtle commands other-where, let ſuch be cenſured, <hi>Put away from your ſelves ſuch a perſon.</hi> The ſame ground or reaſon that will exclude an unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man, will exclude the regenerate, and no other. From whence likewiſe, I ſhall take away this argument from the hands of my proper oppoſers. If the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of perſons from the Lords Supper upon this ground or account; that the Apoſtle commands thoſe that come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould examine themſelves and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Lords body, be a paſtoral duty, as theſe think, (and indeed ſo far as it is done barely on this ground in infants and diſtracted perſons (who being not
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170195:59"/>bound hereunto through incapacity of reaſon are refuſed) it is no other) Then muſt not excluſion of ignorant and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous perſons ſtand upon this ground with the Presbyterians; for that is an act, that cannot be done according to them (as <hi>Beza</hi> fore-quoted) but by the power of juriſdiction. This is, what hath at large been ſaid before Suſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Sacrament, muſt not be held upon any argument from the nature of the ordinance, but from diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is manifeſt that the ſame grace is required of a perſon to be accepted of God in one part of Gods worſhip, as in another. The Scripture requires us expreſly to pray in faith, in love, with underſtanding, and the like, when it does not expreſly but by conſequence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand us ſo to receive; and as for due preparation, or ſelf-examination, and a right diſcernment of the Lord in his worſhip, who will deny it to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in every ordinance, by the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence as in the Sacrament it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe? It cannot therefore be ſaid, that the debarring of ſcandalous or ignorant perſons from the Sacrament, is a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-reſult
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170195:59"/>from the nature of that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and the requiſites to it (which is the whole can be pleaded to make this a paſtoral duty) any more than from prayer and other Ordinances. It is true, we may ſuppoſe, according to the ratity &amp; ſolemnity of an Ordinance, our addreſſes to it may and ought to be more ſolemn, but yet is the Ordinance alike otherwiſe, as to the nature and requiſits to it; and not to be preferred before others, to the breeding ſuch a ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious conceit on the ſpirits of men, that looks to me, like to bowing at the name of Jeſus, and not at the name of Chriſt, God, and the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is not the part of Paſtors to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelves with keeping men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the Sacrament without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding unto cenſure and debarring them other communion (at leaſt that of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon familiarity) to make them aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. I know many happily may be ready to think thus: The Scripture commands ſuch and ſuch ſhould be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, caſt out of the Church and a voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; Now ſeeing we cannot proceed ſo farre, it is good to doe ſomething towards it, we will keep them from the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170195:60"/>Sacrament, and that will be well. But under favour, I am perſwaded this is a great miſtake and evill, in regard that hereby men doe place a virtue in a meanes of their owne to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert ſinners from their evill wayes. It is true, when men are duly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, convicted, and cenſured as they ought, then is there the virtue of an Ordinance which may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to reduce them; for God hath appointed his Ordinance of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline for this purpoſe to bring men to repentance.</p>
               <p>On the contrary, for men to make a buſineſſe onely of keeping people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from this part of Gods ſervice, without diſcipline, how can any ſuch fruit be expected by it? Can men or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain or ſet up themſelves a reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Ordinance? If they doe, How ſhall they give a power and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to it for this effect? Let thoſe Miniſters conſider that have kept ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo many away, even whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations from the Sacrament for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years together, what are the fruits they have reaped by it. Are their people indeed ever the better for it?
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170195:60"/>Does it not rather ſerve only to breed indignation to themſelves, make their Suſpenſion to be flighted, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelf to be neglected; ſo that the moſt of their people care not at all to come thither? If this indeed be the fruit, then will I thus argue. The Ordinances of God, as excluſion from the Church and Sacrament is one, are to be uſed only for Edification, and not deſtruction. But to exclude men the Sacrament without diſcipline, without a due legal conviction and authority, does not tend to their edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but in all this, to their deſtruction. Or thus, The Lord Jeſus commands us expreſly not to give holy things to doggs and ſwine, (as before.) But to uſe ſuſpenſion without diſcipline, or a due authoritative ſentence, as ſhould put a reverence on it, is but likely to caſt it to ſuch, as will tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon it, and turn again and rent the doer. And conſequently therfore, unles Miniſters will purpoſely goe about to make men dogs and ſwine, that elſe would not be ſo in the ſenſe of this text, they are bound
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170195:61"/>directly (at leaſt, when they ſee plainly this is like to be the iſſue) by this very precept of Chriſt (which is that happily ſcruples them main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the contrary) to forbear Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion, till they can uſe it to edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:170195:61"/>
               <head>SECT. 14.</head>
               <p>THeſe two queſtions being laid downe, with my judgement thereof, there will remain two things onely for the compleating my mind in this controverſie. The one is, whereas I hold in the firſt que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, that no argument from the nature of the Sacrament alone, without diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, will be of validity for Suſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it may be required that ſomething be condeſcended to the tenderneſſe of moſt mens ſpirits and practice herein before cenſure. The other is, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I hold in the ſecond queſtion, that thoſe arguments alone are valid for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion from the Sacrament, that reſpect it only as a part of Church-commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and conſequently that a perſon muſt be excommunicate, or excluded Church-communion in general, or elſe he cannot be legally excluded the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, it may be required that there be ſome <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſome ſalve found out
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170195:62"/>here alſo for the abatement of ſo much rigor in cenſure, that a perſon may be permitted ſome of the Ordinances, as the Word, while he is debarred the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and no breach be made on ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication.</p>
               <p>If theſe two things can but be done with reaſonable ſatisfaction, I hope it will ſerve to take away the prejudice of many ſober and moderate ſpirits from my opinion; the drift whereof is not at all to doe the pious Miniſtry any harm (let not my brethren think ſo) in obſtructing their care and inſpection over their flocks, but to bind up their broken hearts with a grounded ſupport, that in what they do, and cannot but do, in admiſſion of their people, (the moſt whereof are unregenerate perſons, and ſo in their ſenſe unworthy) they may do with a ſure foot and ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. <hi>My great buſineſs,</hi> I may ſay truly (with pious Mr. <hi>Blake, Cov: Seal.</hi> ch. 7. ſect. 15. p. 247. in what I have written about this matter together with him) <hi>hath been for their comfort and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement that give admittance, that their benefiting is poſſible, that are thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:170195:62"/>
               <p>And yet by the way I would not be taxed for the opinion of a promiſcuous admittance, which I do not own, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the diſtinction thereof into <hi>Erastian</hi> and orthodox, as before; An <hi>Eraſtian</hi> promiſcuous communion I declare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, as much, and I think ſomething more than Mr. <hi>Blake;</hi> but for an Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Free-admiſſion, the end whereof is to advance diſcipline, not depoſe it, I confeſſe it is what I think ſhould be maintained, being bold to ſay this one thing in reference to that worthy man now named; that an Anti-<hi>Erastian</hi> free-admiſſion will be found I believe at laſt to ſtand a great deal better, both with the Churches peace and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy of Scripture, than a kind of <hi>Eraſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> indiſciplinary Suſpenſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:170195:63"/>
               <head>SECT. 15:</head>
               <p>FIrſt then for ſome condeſcenſion in the former queſtion, how farre thoſe that are more tender in their ſpirits and practice may goe towards with-holding the Sacrament from ſuch they conceive unqualified, as ignorant or ſcandalous, before cenſure, I have touched at in my <hi>Rejoynder,</hi> p. 82, 83. 111, 112. where diſtinguiſhing between what is to be condeſcended to as prudential, and what to be yielded as neceſſary; between what is done by way of advice, and by way of compulſion; between forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and excluſion: I doe acknowledg it is a rule to be allowed in affirmative precepts, that though they doe bind <hi>ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> they do not bind <hi>ad ſemper,</hi> at all times. Upon which account I take it to be lawfull for a man that is obliged, and hath a right to an ordinance, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the ſame upon a juſt occaſion; which (I think) may be, as upon other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>Numb.</hi> 9.10. ſo much more up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170195:63"/>pious ends regarding preparation, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.24. Upon this ſame ground then I humbly conceive, that a Miniſter looking into the ſtate of his flock, and finding ſome ignorant and ſcandalous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, though he cannot take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf to exclude them the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before cenſure, he may proceed ſo far towards it, that beſides the rebuking of them ſharply, he may admoniſh or adviſe them to forbear the ordinance at preſent, ſo long as he judges it in pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to be a means to make them come the more prepared to the next Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; what hinders but the Miniſter may ſtretch himſelf even to the utmoſt end of his line of doctrin, when he ſtands there, and knows that he is ſtill without the line of juriſdiction? And this I conceive may ſatisfie the conſcientious in this thing, putting into their hands as much advantage as a ſingle paſtor can have to the following them with inſtruction for the good of their ſouls, which is that I ſuppoſe they only aim at in this matter; and if it were any thing elſe, it is fit they ſhould never obtain it.</p>
               <p>Only I muſt adde here that I ſuffer not in my principles; It is not becauſe
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170195:64"/>I think receiving is no duty unto ſuch, for this, I conceive, were evil to hold; Nor becauſe I think it not appointed for edification unto ſuch; for thoſe arguments that reverend Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> hath put in, to prove the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a means of grace to the unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate within the Church (<hi>Cov. Seal.</hi> ch. 7. ſect. 13.) muſt needs reach, and be cogent for theſe alſo, as they are Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members, although he would not have them; Nor becauſe I think that ſuch are in an utter incapacity to be edified by it, as infants and the diſtracted are, (wherein the formentioned learned man places his whole ground of diſſent he hath from me in this point) ſeeing the Sacrament through the word (and the word goes along with it) doth teach as for the one, and convince of ſin as for the other, as is ſaid before, and granted by him. That it is a teaching Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, <hi>mediante verbo,</hi> even at the preſent for the ignorant; I pray let me but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this one thing, Were not thoſe words of our Lord to his diſciples <hi>[This is my body broken for you, This is the New Testament in my blood which was ſhed for remiſſion of ſinnes]</hi> teaching words, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170195:64"/>forming them of his death, and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our redemption? Who can deny this? And were not the diſciples igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant at that time, of his death, and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of our redemption? Compare <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.31, 32. <hi>Lu.</hi> 9.44, 45. with <hi>Lu.</hi> 24. 7, 8. <hi>Io.</hi> 20.9. and what then will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low for the ignorant, is cleer. That it is a ſin-aggravating Ordinance, and ſo a ſoul-humbling, heart-breaking Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the ſinner, Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and I ſo well agree, <hi>Rejoynd.</hi> p. 235, 236. with <hi>Cov. Seal.</hi> p. 204. that it needs no argument; and then what follows for the ſcandalous is as clear likewiſe. It is not therefore, I ſay, for theſe cauſes, that I allow thus much; but it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, becauſe I think that no leſſe can be denied to belong to the Miniſter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſcore of prudence only. That there is a poſſibility (upon what is ſaid) of edification unto all intelligent Church-members, though ſcandalous, (<hi>Cov. Seal.</hi> p. 240.) or ignorant (p. 233.) Mr. <hi>B.</hi> cannot ingenuouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: and that there is not that moral pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability or likelihood hereof, as upon their further inſtruction and preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I do grant; From both which then
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170195:65"/>the plain reaſon will ariſe, why ſuch may in prudence be adviſed to forbear the Sacrament at preſent, when yet it muſt be held faſt, that there is no neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity on the conſcience, <hi>ſimpliciter,</hi> for the ir excluſion.</p>
               <p>To ſpeak a little more my thoughts freely, I conceive it to be a <hi>Magnale</hi> in the wiſdom of the Church, which hath ever kept up ſome more ſolemn times for the putting in mind of her members to ſhrift or addreſſe their ſouls to God in a more peculiar manner at ſome ſeaſons above others, to make uſe of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to this end; inſomuch, that though the primitive Chriſtians broke bread every week, and ſometimes daily, yet hath it been the uſe of after Ages to celebrate this Ordinance more rarely, that the ſolemnity and rarity (thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. giving help here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto) might have this deſired work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people. Upon this ſame ſcore I do conceive this condeſcenſion may take place in allowing that a forbearance of the Lords Supper be adviſed many times to unprepared, unfit perſons, when we judge it in Chriſtian prudence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible through a more ſolemn addreſs
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170195:65"/>thereunto, towards a farther improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof for their ſouls; And ſo may the ſame be aſſerted happily (as I judge of it) <hi>Ex quadam conveniontia, Ob ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorem reverentiam,</hi> as the School-men ſpeak in ſome other caſes about this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; When as I am perſwaded o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe there is the ſame outward pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, aed the ſame inward qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions held forth alike in the Scripture unto this and other Ordinances. And this for my firſt conceſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:170195:66"/>
               <head>SECT. 16.</head>
               <p>SEcondly then, for ſome <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or condeſcenſion in the latter queſtion, that the excommunicate perſon may not be ſo turned out from all the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, (though he be turned out from them, and that alike too, from one as well as the other, in a ſort) but that he may have admittance to ſome of them, upon an account which may be juſtifiable, for the gaining of his ſoul and yet without the introducing of this leſſer cenſure of ſuſpenſion, into the diſcipline of man, which is not in the diſcipline of Chriſt, or the Scripture I have ſpoken more at large in my <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynd.</hi> part. 2. ſect. 1. See particularly <hi>p</hi> 87. &amp; 149. Where having ſhewn that Church-cenſure or Excommunication does reſerre to Church-communion in general, and conſequently that a perſon excommunicate is caſt out from every part thereof, and ſo from all the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances as well as the Sacrament, I do
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170195:66"/>humbly offer this diſtinction, of a Real, and Relative excluſion. A real excluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is an excluſion of a man from a thing, ſo that he cannot by any means partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate of the thing; A relative excluſion, is the excluſion of a man from his relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to a thing, or his right of priviledge in it, whether he yet otherwiſe poſſeſſes the thing or not. Now that which we admit Heathen to, in receiving them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, I think we caſt them out from, in excommunicating them; But we admit not perſons to an actual hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Word, or participating ſuch or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances as they did, and might attend before; but we admit them into a ſtate and relation, whereby the ordinances belong to them, with a difference of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge from the world, and as they par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took of them while they were without; They were then indeed admitted to the Word, and it may be Prayer, to bring them in, as they ought, yet neither one nor the other Ordinance did belong to them by way of advantage, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.2. or propriety, as externally in covenant, in Chriſt, redeemed ſanctified, &amp;c. as they doe, being members. Conſequently therefore, my thoughts are, that though
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170195:67"/>Excommunication cuts off a perſon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latively from all the Ordinances (from one alike as well as the other, in the ſenſe now ſpoken) and does cut off a man really from that Ordinance, the actual participation whereof is <hi>peculiar</hi> to that relation, as the Sacrament; Yet this Relative excluſion does not neceſſarily inferre a Real excluſion of a man from thoſe other Ordinances, as the Word and Prayer, which may be partaken of out of that relation. And ſo here will ariſe that, which may give content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; to wit, that upon this it ſhall be left in the Churches hands <hi>by way of Mitigation,</hi> to admit the Excommunicate hereunto, whether one or more (or none) of them, as ſhe ſees it fit to uſe ſeverity or indulgence to bring the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to repentance.</p>
               <p>It is manifeſt, that the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church was wont to permit an Heathen, or thoſe that were <hi>without,</hi> to be preſent in their aſſemblies at the Word if not at Prayer and ſome other Ordinances, for their conviction, as appears, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. According to this preſident, it is my opinion then, in ſhort, that a perſon excommunicate may be
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170195:67"/>admitted to an Ordinance, or Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as an Heathen (into which condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he is expreſly caſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.) when yet he is cut off from all his priviledge and intereſt in them as a member. And this, I ſuppoſe, will even ſerve the turn of my very adverſaries, and yet be no diſhight or prejudice to that latitude of Excommunication which the truth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates, and muſt be maintained, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my opinion.</p>
               <p>In fine, two things are objected againſt me by my Oppoſers, which methinks do even quite take off one another. In the former queſtion it is objected that my doctrine is looſe, in that it admits of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very intelligent Church-member to the Sacrament, before cenſure; To which I anſwer, That doctrine about admiſſion that maintaines Excommunication, in point of offending, cannot be looſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the offender; and if a man have not offended, I mean ſo far as to deſerve cenſure, the Miniſter can but admoniſh and adviſe, he can go no further; and here how much I allow upon the ſcore of paſtoral diſcretion is declared, And why ſhould any more be deſired? In the ſecond queſtion it is objected, my
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170195:68"/>doctrine is too ſevere, bloody, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, in that thoſe perſons which it cuts off from the Sacrament, it cuts off from all other parts of Church-communion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; To this I anſwer, It is true, it does do thus indeed according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but let this be underſtood aright and candidly of this Relative exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, (here declared likewiſe) and then I hope all will be reconciled and ſatisfied.</p>
               <p>And thus I have now finiſhed my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, endeavouring to keep in a way of moderation, that I might avoid the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities of others. I have not in any thing, I ſuppoſe, departed from the Scripture as my Guide; and yet in every thing come up as near as I can to thoſe that are againſt me, to content them. I do not know how it may be taken, but it ſhall ſuffice me that I have in the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of my intention (ſo far as I can judg of my own heart) propoſed my thoughts, leaving others to their own. The Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches peace is the thing I have aimed at, without hindring (but happily furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring) her reformation. <hi>If I have done well, and as is fitting to the matter, it is that I deſired, if I have done but ſlenderly and meanly, it is what I could attain unto.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Deo gloria.</closer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. H.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:170195:68"/>
            <head>A POST SCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are yet ſome things I ſhal make, bold to trouble thee to read in this place, becauſe I would not have the Diſcourſe it ſelf to ſwel any bigger tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it has don. If thou thinkſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> long, thou mayeſt let them alone if thou wilt. I know well that this controverſie is not about any funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, but that, as brethren, we may bear well enough with one another that differ in it, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, in regard of practice, it is even neceſſary at leaſt for moſt that are of the Ministry to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht concerning the ſame, or elſe perhaps, it might have been long enough before ſome ſhould have thought it fit to meddle any more with it. What I have done here in this laſt book, I offer to them chiefly, and thee that haſt ſtudied the point; what I have done in my firſt book, to the many.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>[1.]</hi> Whereas in my undertaking this Subject, I choſe thoſe words, <hi>Doe this, Drink ye all of it,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170195:69"/>And they all drank of it,</hi> in that text <hi>Mar. 14. 23.</hi> for my ground, which many think might have been more ſoundly choſen: I deſire the ſtrength thereof may be laid in thoſe two things which have been touched <hi>Sect. 10.</hi> but I am not ſatisfied without ſpeaking a little farther thereof, with thy leave to have it noted by ſuch. The firſt is, that we have here, as in the other Evangeliſts, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Sacrament, wherein there is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect precept to the Church, <hi>Doe this,</hi> with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent thereof expreſſed, <hi>Drink ye all of ir.</hi> The words are directed in general to the diſciples, as diſciples, and conſequently all that are diſciples (ſuppoſe them in a capacity of reaſon to uſe it) come under a right of Obligation to uſe the ſame. It is objected, <hi>By all, is meant no more than All preſent.</hi> But this is too overly, the precept I hope, does ſo concern the diſciples preſent, as that St. <hi>Paul</hi> makes theſe very words of the inſtitution obtigatory to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and to us all as a ſtanding Ordinance till Chriſt come, <hi>1 Cor. 11. 26.</hi> It is manifeſt then that theſe words, as the precept of Chriſt, are delivered to the diſciples in bebalf of the Church, whereof themſelves were a repreſentative part. Now then I ask, whether as Repreſentatives of the Church inviſible, or viſible? if you will ſay of the Church inviſible to make the command only to the regenerate and elect, it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable; for all the Ordinances are delivered to the Church as viſible, <hi>Heb. 9.19. Rom. 3.2.</hi> and we ſuppoſe <hi>Judas</hi> was amongſt them. But if they were here Repreſentatives of the Church, as viſible, it muſt follow, that all thoſe who are of the viſible Church, (and in capacity of the obligation) are berchy obliged to this Ordinance. It is not ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentative to ſay here, none of theſe diſciples
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170195:69"/>were ignorant or ſcandalous (which yet I think is untrue) becauſe they were repreſentatives of the Church, not as men unspotted with ignorance or ſcandal, any more than as Apoſtles, but as they were members thereof, viſible members, diſciples, Chriſtians. <hi>Id veiò concedimus,</hi> ſaies <hi>Bezs,</hi> (De Presb. &amp; Ex. p. <hi>27. with 23.) quòd Chriſtus inter ſuos diſcipulos coenam inſtituens manifeſtè oftendìt coenae celebrationem illis convenire</hi> (which is inciuded in <hi>ſolis illis) qui Chriſti ſe diſcipulos profiteantur;</hi> and Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> (Caſe conſ. B. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>10,</hi>) laies this down for his firſt rule, <hi>Every man of years living in the Church, and being baptized, is bound in conſcience by the commandement to uſe the Supper.</hi> Now whiles my adverſaries are forced to fly off here, and confine the precept to the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate only, we may eaſily ſee both where our bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom lies, and alſo how firm it is. The ſecond thing I build on in this text, is, That together with the precept, we have the example of <hi>Iudas,</hi> who is ſat down with the twelve, <hi>Mat. 26.20.</hi> and his hand at the table, <hi>Luke 22.21.</hi> It is objected, that <hi>Judas</hi> was a cloſe hypocrite, his villany ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and unknown, and ſo this preſident will make nothing to our purpoſe. But under favour, ſuch as ſay ſo, are miſtaken, for though this anſwer ſhould ſuffice (which I think it does not) as to the part of the admitters, in regard Chriſt acting (ſay they) as a Miniſter, was not to take notice of what he knew of <hi>Judas</hi> as he was God: yet it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that it reaches not the matter at all as to the receivers themſelves, who neverthleſs for all this, as for their own parts, will be bound to receiving. though they be ſuch as <hi>Judas</hi> was, that is, at leaſt unregenerate, if not ſcandalous alſo. It may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170195:70"/>as to the part of the admitters, that Chriſt knew of <hi>Judas</hi> compact (which no doubt was a high ſcandal in its ſelf, being inductive of ſin and ruine to the Jews, with whom he dealt) not only as God, but as man likewiſe, becauſe as man, he was a Prophet, <hi>Deut. 18, 15.</hi> and that God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head that dwelt in him bodily, revealed this to him; Now I argue, if it was Chriſts duty to have excluded <hi>Judas</hi> from the Paſſeover, if a man had revealed this to him, how much more must be have done it when the God-head revealed it to him, whoſe teſtimony is above all mens in the world? But I ſhall chuſe to lay my ſtrength here (as I ſay) as to the part of the receivers, &amp; that from Chriſts acting, not as a mere man, but as Mediator. As the Lord Jeſus does inſtitute the Sacrament, and give the precept, he muſt do it unqueſtionably as mediator; It is God only can give laws to bind the conſcience: Now in the inſtitution and giving the precept, he directs the ſame to all preſent, and ſo to <hi>Judas</hi> amongſt the reſt, from whence ariſes an obligation from the Lord irrefragably upon <hi>Judas,</hi> as well as on the others, to actual receiving; what Chriſt bids him expreſly do among them, muſt be his duty; and conſequently, while a man is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, though unregenerate, as <hi>Judas</hi> was, that does not unduty him to uſe the Supper. And then let us hear what Dr. <hi>Diake</hi> himſelf, who herein throughly looks to the foundation, will tell us. <hi>Let but Mr. H.</hi> (ſays be <hi>p. 116.) prove that actual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving is a debt on the part of a natural man, and he will yield the cauſe to us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">[2.] Whereas it is denied, notwithſtanding this text and others by us alleadged, that there is no precept nor preſident in Scripture for the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Sacrament to all, (Mr. <hi>Coll. ch. 5.</hi>)
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170195:70"/>I deſire theſe two Trules may be laid, <hi>1.</hi> that Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and receiving being <hi>Relata,</hi> all thoſe texts that prove it the duty of any to receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, does <hi>eo nomine</hi> oblige the Miniſter to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it to them, or admit them, becauſe <hi>Poſito uno relatorum, ponitur alterum. 2.</hi> That we are to look upon all the Ordinances of God unto his Church, as univerſal, obliging every member in particular to wait upon them, unleſs where the Scripture it ſelf layes ſome reſtriction or limitation; the reaſon is, becauſe it is preſumption in any to limit that which Gad hath not reſtrained. And then I do aſſert hereupon, that there is as many Scripture-precepts and preſidents to deliver the Sacrament to all, as to any, ſuppoſing them within the Church, and neither unintelligent, or excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, as we entend the queſtion; for ſuch as are Heathen, <hi>Exod. 12.43, 48.</hi> or have not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and diſcernment, <hi>1 Cor. 11. 28, 29.</hi> or are under cenſure, <hi>1 Cor. 5. 13.</hi> are debarr'd (we all grant) by the Scriptures quoted. There are two inſtances only, beſides the precept and preſident in the former text, I will here mention. The one is, the inſtance of the Paſſeover, where <hi>all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Iſrael, every man,</hi> Ex. <hi>12.3, 47, 50. from Dan to Berſheba, 2</hi> Chr. <hi>30.5. all their males every year,</hi> Exod. <hi>34.23.</hi> Deut. <hi>16. 16. All the children of the captivity,</hi> to name that text, <hi>Ezra 6.21.</hi> becauſe by ſome it is allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt us; that is, all the Jews that return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, without exception, <hi>and all ſuch as had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated themſelves unto them from the filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the heathen;</hi> that is, all their proſelytes alſo (the filthineſſe of the heathen was their idols) <hi>did eat,</hi> and were ſo commanded. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which I would chiefty have obſerved, that
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170195:71"/>made any <hi>Iſraelite</hi> uncapable of partaking thereof, but that which made a godly man uncapable, and ſuch, no more uncapable of this, than of other the holy things. And this was Levitical uncleanneſs, whereof while the queſtion is propoſed to <hi>Moſes, Num. 9.</hi> whether ſuch ſhould eat of it or no, it is plain (in the chapter) that for the reſt to eat thereof, was out of queſtion. The other inſtance is that of <hi>1 Cor. 10.1, 2, 3, 4.</hi> as I have preſt it in my firſt book. <hi>They all eat of the Manna, and drank of the rock, which was Chriſt.</hi> The main anſwer given by <hi>Beza, Gilleſpy, Philip Goodwin, Rutherford, Dr. Drake,</hi> and which all have, is, that <hi>all the Iſraclites were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted here, becauſe this water and manna was their corporal food, without which they could not live.</hi> But herein lyes the force of what we urge, to wit, Why ſhould the Lord make that ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary food of theirs, without which they could not live, to be Sacramental, if to eat and drink of Chriſt ſacramentally, was not a priviledge in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the Church? The main thing alleaged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Free-admiſſion, is the holineſs of that, whereunto Sacramental ſigus do relate, and the indispoſition of the viſibly unworthy to partake thereof; Now ſayes the Apoſtle, the <hi>Iſraelites all of them,</hi> yet many of them unworthy (in our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries ſenſe) <hi>did drink of the rock, which was Chriſt,</hi> and it was the Lords will they ſhould do ſo, for therefore he made that food (I ſay) which all were to live by, Sacramental. Beſides, if it were ſuch a grievous ſin, as murdering the Lord of glory, or being guilty of his bloud, to drink of Chriſt ſymholically, without ſuch and ſuch qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, as ſome do ſtill speak, then ſhould theſe <hi>Iſraelites</hi> (as I have ſaid in my <hi>Rejoynd.</hi>) have
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170195:71"/>rather ſamiſhed their bodies, than have eat and drank the damnation of their ſouls; whereas we find that the ſons of <hi>Aaron, Lev. 22.23.</hi> were not to eat of the holy things during their Levitical uncleanneſs, though it was their appointed food, which <hi>Gilleſpy</hi> himſelf notes, <hi>p. 97. Exemplo Iſraëlitarum</hi> (ſaies <hi>Muſculus,</hi> in <hi>Pſ. 105. v. 39.) Apoſtolus admonet, uſum externorum Sacramentorum, talem eſſe, ut neminem juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficet, poſſing; ab omnibus promiſcuè exerce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">[3.] Whereas it is laid down, by my adverſaries, as their main hold, that viſible worthineſs is the rule of admiſſion, as viſible unworthineſs or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitneſs the rule of Suspenſion; I ſhall think ſit to propoſe, or oppoſe theſe three things. 1. Take all the viſible worthineſs in the world, it can amount to no more than an external covenant-relation, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominating the ſubjects <hi>quoad homines,</hi> Saints, Believers, Chriſtians. Now who ſhall define us theſe covenant-relatives, either this judgement of men, or the open plain determination of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures? 2. If we go on this ground of covenant-relation, we go on a certain judgement, every one knows who are externally in covenant, or Church-members, but if we go on viſible worthineſs, as a third thing (between this and truth of grace) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct here from, we muſt go on continual uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, as without Scripture. 3. This rule of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible worthineſs, is bottom'd on real worthineſs, which it ſuppoſeth in the receiver, as neceſſarily antecedent to the Sacraments. Now then I argue, either the manifeſtations hereof (for viſible fitneſs or worthineſs being their rule of admitting people, that fitneſs muſt be tryed, and that by evidence) upon which the Sacrament muſt be adminiſtred,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170195:72"/>are either infallible or certain, and then no hypocrite can ever receive, or be admitted, which is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs untrue; Or probable only, and conjectural, and then none can in faith adminiſter to another, becauſe he cannot he aſſured by all thoſe evidences or manifeſtations, that the party hath that in him which is neceſſarily and eſſentially held pre-requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to receiving. The Sacraments cannot be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred according to rule, unleſs they have their neceſſary pre-requiſites, or eſſentials; nor in faith, unleſs the Miniſter be aſſured they have their eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentials. And therefore it is not real worthineſs, or truth of grace, as to the receivers own part; or viſible worthineſſe as to the admitters part, but covenant-relation in both, is the very ground in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed both of adminiſtring and receiving; alwayes remembring, that our queſtion truly is not concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning what is required of the receiver in order to other ends, that he may be ſaved (ſo truth of grace and final perſeverance too, is neceſſary) but what is neceſſarily antecedent to the obtaining the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ordinance, and to the validity thereof. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Reader to obſerve this well, that be may know clearly how to put a ſound difference between theſe two things, to wit, between what is required of the receiver in his coming, or that comes to the Sacrament, and what is ſo required to receiving, as that elſe be must not come. As to the former, we are to preſs upon men all thoſe Sacramental quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications which are laid down ordinarily by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, as being neceſſary to the obtaining the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual benefits of Chriſt held forth in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But as for the latter, we muſt take heed what we preſs upon any, leſt we preſſe them only to the omiſſion of their duty. Even as we are to preſs upon men who hear and pray, that they pray
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170195:72"/>and hear with underſtanding, faith, love, humility, and other graces (as they are to receive) and that if they do not, they ſin in their hearing and prayer; Yet muſt not we preſs this ſo, that if they have not theſe qualifications, they may not hear nor pray; this were to preſs them to iniquity, for the avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of partial, to run into total diſobedience. By this diſtinction then we ſhall underſtand, both how to preſs the Sacrament on our people that neglect it; <hi>The man that bringeth not the offering of the Lord in his appointed ſeaſon, ſhall be cut off,</hi> Numb. 9. and how to preſs our people to a worthy behaviour, that come to it. And both theſe, I think, ought to be preſſed together, the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Ordinances are the means if any have not theſe graces, to excite their hearts unto them; for whatſoever ſome of our late Divines may ſay, when thoſe two great Reformers <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Swinglius</hi> met at the Synod of <hi>Marparge,</hi> however they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd otherwiſe about the Sacrament, they agreed perfectly in theſe two things; both <hi>that the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament was neceſſary unto every Chriſtian man; and that the uſe of it was to the ſame effect with the Word, ordained of God, that thereby infirm conſciences might be ſtirred to belief, by the holy Ghoſt.</hi> See Book of Martyrs, Vol. 2. <hi>p. 87.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">[4.] Whereas there are certain places urged by many for the ſecluſion of the morally unclean, from the Paſſeover, which Mr. <hi>Coll.</hi> hath in part hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up, <hi>p. 101.</hi> from <hi>Gilleſpy, B. 1. c. 9.</hi> to wit, <hi>Iſa. 1.10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. Jer. 7.9, 10, 11. Pſ. 50.16. Pſ. 118.19, 20. Pſ. 15.1. Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra 6.21.2 Chron. 23.19. Deur. 23.18. Hag. 2.11, 12, 13, 14. Ezek. 22.26. Ezek. 44.7, 9. Ezek, 23.39.</hi> I ſhall think fit to ſpeak
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170195:73"/>ſomething briefly to theſe Scriptures. For the 3 firſt, <hi>Iſa. 1.10 — 15. Jer. 7.9. — 11. Pſ. 50 16.</hi> It is plain that theſe texts speak of Prayer, the Word, and the whole worſhip of God general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their ſolemn aſſemblies, as well as the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and therefore muſt be underſtood ſo, as that though the manner of their comming be reproved in ſuch a patherical veine, a DESC="foreign", as it is, the matter nevertheleſs in the ſubſtance was not to be left undone. The rule is this, when an action hath evil in its own ſubſtance, it is to be omitted; but when the action is of it ſelf the matter of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and hath evil externally caſt on it by the agent that doth it, here the action is not to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, but the agent to be reformed. See <hi>Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds 3 Treat. p. 248.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Pemble</hi> in Fol. Vind. Gov. p. <hi>82.</hi> To the two next texts, <hi>Pſ. 118. 19, 20. Pſ. 15.1.</hi> I anſwer, as to the former, that on the contrary hand the righteous here are ſpoken of as ſuch only that could come to the Lords houſe with acceptation of their perſons in their ſervices, but it does not follow therefore that the unrighteous muſt not come to do any ſervice at the temple. To argue thus, <hi>This is the gate into which the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall enter;</hi> therefore the unrighteous were never to come there, is me-thinks juſt like the Jews, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. who when the Law commanded, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour,</hi> collected, <hi>and hate thine enemy.</hi> For the text following, <hi>Ezra 6.21.</hi> I have mentioned it in the ſecond thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as full and plain for us. To the next, 2 <hi>Chr. 23.19.</hi> I have anſwered in <hi>4.</hi> or <hi>5.</hi> particulars, <hi>Rejoynd. p. 45.</hi> Only whereas in the laſt of them I am acquainted from Mr. <hi>Coll. (p. ibidem)</hi> that though the Paſſeover was eaten in their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yet it was killed in the Temple. I ſhould
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170195:73"/>have thanked him for his learning, if he had not neglected to acquaint me alſo out of the ſame Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor he quotes there, that the Jews being diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at this ſolemnitive into their Paſchal ſocieties, it was but one only of every ſociety that carried the lamb to the temple to be killed, and then the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, I hope, remains ſtill as for the reſt, that is, the generality, how could the ſetting porters at the gates of the temple be any hindrance to them in eating the Paſſeover, that was eaten in their privat houſes? For the text enſuing, <hi>Deur. 23.18.</hi> I think but few are like to be much moved by it. It follows not, becauſe the hire of a harlot was not to be brought for a vow into the houſe of the Lord, that therefore the harlot her ſelf might not come thither upon other ſervice. It is plain, that the Phariſees brought the woman taken in adultery to christ in the temple, <hi>Jo. 8.2, 3.</hi> It is anſwered, <hi>By the temple we muſt underſtand the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mural, or outer Court only.</hi> But I pray who was there, to ſay ſo? Again it is anſwered, ſhe was brought thither <hi>ad poenam, to be judged,</hi> well, but I pray then how could the morally unclean be thought to defile the temple, when their place of Judicature unto which they brought their capital offenders, was in the temple? The Prieſts would not receive back <hi>Judas</hi> money into the Treaſury, but they refuſed not <hi>Judas</hi> himſelf to come to them within the Sanctuary. To the next text, <hi>Hag. 2. 11. — 14.</hi> I anſwer, Though moral uncleanneſs is compared here with levitical, yet did it not defile the holy things, as legal did, <hi>nullum ſimile eſt idem,</hi> but in ſome other conſideration, to wit, every thing is unclean morally to the unclean, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Tit. 1.15.</hi> in this ſenſe, that ſo long as the best actions proceed not from a ſanctified heart,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170195:74"/>they are ſinne, there will be ſin in dominion as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the manner of performance of them. See my <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynd.</hi> more fully, <hi>p. 115, 116.</hi> Now in this ſenſe however all the ordinances and all a mans duties become unclean to him, this text forbids not, but they muſt be done; for elſe, ſo long as a man is unſanctified he muſt do nothing, becauſe all his ſervices, <hi>all the works of his hands,</hi> as every holy thing, is polluted (as to this ſenſe) and profaned by him. In ſhort, There is a defilement of a mans ſervice, ſo as to cauſe them to be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or ſo as not to cauſe them to be omitted; Moral uncleanneſs may be ſaid to defile the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, as all things are ſaid to be unclean to the wicked, <hi>Tit. 1.15.</hi> yet ſo, that theſe ſervices are not to be omitted, and a man to do nothing. (<hi>See Pemble</hi> before-quoted.) But it does not defile them ſo as legal pollution did defile the Sanctuary, that was, ſo as ſuch might not do their ſervice in the Sanctuary. The Sadduces were groſſly wicked perſons, as to their opinions, and yet did not the Phariſees ever queſtion their comming to the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for the ſervice of God; and when the Jews look'd on <hi>Paul,</hi> as a moſt vile notorious perſon that did live, yet they find no fault at all with him for his own comming into the temple, <hi>Act. 21.24. — 29.</hi> (nor could they ſure upon this ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe it is not likely the Apoſtles then would have adviſed him ſuch a way to avoid their fury) while they made ſuch an intollerable stir only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuppoſal that he had brought ſome <hi>Greekes</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. For the two next texts, <hi>Ez. 22.26. Ez. 44.7.9.</hi> I conceive they are palpably wreſted i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Moral uncleanneſs. By the <hi>holy,</hi> is meant the Jew, or circumciſed, <hi>Ezra 9.2. Deut. 14.2.</hi> (who are again divided into the clean, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170195:74"/>that is, levitically) and by the <hi>profane ſtranger,</hi> the uncircumciſed. This ſtranger was their proſelyte of the gate, who might not come into the Temple before his circumciſion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is called uncircumciſed in heart, as well as in fleſh, that being yet uncircumciſed in fleſh he durſt offer to do it. I know <hi>Gilleſpy, p. 88.</hi> ſtands much on the word <hi>Nor, Ez. 44.9;</hi> But what if this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſjunctive <hi>Nor,</hi> prove to be the conjunctive <hi>And</hi> in the Original (the words directly render'd running thus; <hi>Every ſtranger uncircumciſed in fleſh, and uncircumciſed in Heart, ſhall not enter, &amp;c.</hi>) what then ſhall we think, to ſee not only <hi>Gilleſpy,</hi> and <hi>Rutherford, (Ch. Gov. p. 246.)</hi> but even the Provincial Aſſembly of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don (Vind. Presb. Gov. p. 54.)</hi> to take up things thus on truſt, one after another? For the laſt text, <hi>Ez. 23.38, 39.</hi> It ſeems to me that the defilement in this place (as in the other) was by their legal, not moral uncleanneſs. For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in <hi>v. 37.</hi> God hath expreſſed their Idolatry and murder, he adds in v. <hi>38. Moreover</hi> (or beſides that) <hi>this they have done unto me,</hi> to wit, defiled my houſe, that is another crime; then in v. <hi>39.</hi> he explains how, <hi>For when they had ſlain their children to their idols, they came the ſame day into my Sanctuary to defile it.</hi> Now it cannot be doubted, but in the ſlaying their chilren to their Idols there muſt neceſſarily be a touching ſomething that was unclean by the dead, which was Levitical pollution, <hi>Num. 22.4.</hi> and ſo herein lay this third crime added to the reſt, that being thus unclean, they came nevertheleſſe into Gods Sanctuary in the ſame day, to profane it. That this is the meaning, theſe words <hi>In the ſame day,</hi> make it clear. I pray mark them, they are
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170195:75"/>twice repeated, both <hi>verſe 38, &amp; 39.</hi> that you may not eſcape the meaning. <hi>Moreover they have defiled my Sanctuary by comming into in the ſame day.</hi> Now why the ſame day? what if it had been the next day, or another after? it had been all one to Moral uncleanneſs. But becauſe of their Legal uncleanneſs, the Law in this caſe expreſſly commanded, that who ſo touched any thing that was unclean by the dead, he was to be unclean til the Even, and not to come into the Sanctuary (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pain of being cut off) before his purification, <hi>Lev. 22. v. 4.</hi> with <hi>v. 6.</hi> I will cloze theſe texts with an obſervation here, to avoid miſconſtruction; It is this, that there are two things ſeem <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or incompatible, and are not ſo, but are both to be held as plainly true. They are theſe, That a perſon though he be ungodly or wicked, may and muſt wait upon the Ordinances, it is his duty that he is bound unto; and yet that ſuch a perſon too may and muſt (upon conviction and cenſure) be excluded; that is; there is nothing in the nature of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, but that ſuch may come to them, being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of God for the working grace and reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the commers; Yet hath the Lord ſet up a power in the Church, whereby theſe perſons upon a due account, ſhall by way of puniſhment be cut off from them: ſuch being the wiſdom of Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments, that both their commiag before cenſure, and their excluſion upon cenſure, are a like means to be uſed, one after another, for the bringing them to repentance. To this purpoſe I cannot paſs in the way, thoſe Texts which <hi>Gilleſpy</hi> mentions, <hi>p. 106, 107.</hi> to prove that ſcandalous ſins do pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, not only a mans ſelf, but the people of God that are in fellowſhip with them, <hi>1 Cor. 5, 6. Heb. 13.15, 16, 2 Pet. 2.13. Jude 13.</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170195:75"/>I anſwer, that this pollution, I take it, is not, <hi>1.</hi> any kind of outward pollution, as under the Law. <hi>2.</hi> Nor any intrinſecal pollution, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, while a mans own conſcience is not defiled. <hi>3.</hi> Nor is it only a bare pollution by evil example, imitation or infection, for ſo the good are not defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; though in part indeed, it is this. But <hi>4.</hi> under favour, that pollution or defilement where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the whole Church and fellowſhip thereof is ſaid defiled or leavened by a ſcandalows ſinner, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that he is to be caſt out from it (especially in the primitive time, when they had their gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Churches amidſt the heathen) is a pollution of diſcredit, diſgrace, and diſreputation which is brought upon the Church; in ſuffering ſuch among them; In regard of which report <hi>(It is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reported, 1 Cor. 5.1.)</hi> ſuch as theſe, are le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, spots, blemiſhes to the whole, beſides the evil inclined following their ſteps. And ſo though I would maintain the Ordinances free from any ſuch pollution by wicked men (as was by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs under the Law) that ſhould neceſſitate all ſuch never to come at them: Yet I do not at all infringe diſcipline; but in the taking off what op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes Free-admiſſion, I leave the grounds ſtill firm (even this alſo from the keeping Church-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip pure in a right ſenſe) for Excomunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>[5.]</hi> Whereas it is commonly urged by the moſt from what is ſpoken, <hi>The morally unclean are worſe than the levitical, if the one were to be kept from the Paſſeover, then much more the other, and ſo from the Sacrament.</hi> I doe humbly conceive, if I may speak freely, that <hi>Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> hath moſt elaborately ſatisfied this argument <hi>(Confir. Theſ. lib. 2. cap. 1.)</hi> for all what
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170195:76"/>
               <hi>Beza, Rutherford,</hi> or <hi>Gilleſpy,</hi> have replyed to him. They indeed do prove, that legal unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was a type of our moral uncleanneſs, which <hi>Eraſtus</hi> denies not, but they do not prove that their excluſion was a type of our Excommunication, which he ſtands upon, much leſſe of Suspenſion, as diſtinct from it, which ſerves me. The type and the thing typed, are not to be made the ſame. <hi>Quod praecipue intendebamus,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>eſt immunditiam legis non ita praefiguraſſe ſcelera, ut in his terris, eodem modo, eadem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poenâ coercenda eſſe concludi poſſit.</hi> For my part, I think that this barr of Levitical uncleanneſs is not to be look'd upon as any cenſure for a crime, (it was a calamity, not a ſin to be a leper) but as a Mandate only for the keeping up that ceremonial outward holineſs, on things, places, perſons, which God was pleaſed to enjoyn under the Law, for what reaſons that infinite wiſdom only knows beſt, that hath now aboliſhed the ſame. That a man who had ſworn, lyed, deceived, or committed a like ſin, might come the ſame day to the holy things and not defile them, and yet that the moſt pious Jew that had but touched any thing unclean, could not come without defilement of them; it is to be reſolved only into the will of God, that would have it ſo, and to inquire farther into the reaſon of this will, (as Mr. <hi>Coll.</hi> does, <hi>p. 100.</hi>) is not to be wiſe unto ſobriety. The force then of this argument as <hi>Eraſtus</hi> has it, will indeed be all one with this, as if a man neatly dreſt, ſhould thus argue; A thief or a drunkard is worſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that man who carries lime or coal; but I muſt take heed of coming near that man, leſt he pollute or ſmut me, therfore I muſt much leſſe come near a wicked, or ſcandalous perſon. It is therefore an ingenuous acknowledgement of that
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170195:76"/>Presbyterian Author, whoſoever he be, that wrot the Vindication of the Antiquaeriſt againſt Mr. <hi>Prynne, p. 7.</hi> where confeſſing ſome arguments indeed uſed for ſuſpenſion to be <hi>weak, For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>thoſe arguments brought from the Ceremonial Law ſeem to me but Ceremonial, not ſubſtantial arguments, and if they prove any thing, I conceive</hi> (pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce tantorum virorum <hi>who make uſe of them</hi>) <hi>they evince rather a ſecluſion from ſpiritual and eternal priviledges, than from outward Goſpel-Ordinances.</hi> And unto this Dr. <hi>Drake</hi> himſelf againſt me, agrees perfectly, <hi>p. 20,</hi> which is according to <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> &amp; the truth, in this particular.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>[6.]</hi> Whereas the foundation I ſtand upon in the main of this dispute, is duty, which muſt n needs be a ſure bottom, in regard that mans im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency or iniquity cannot evacuate Gods autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but the will of God muſt ſtand againſt all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence; and hereupon thoſe that write againſt me, are neceſſitated to aſſert, that it is the duty of none to receive the Sacrament, but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate only, which are happily here and there one in a congregation. I ſhall appeal to the conſciences of thoſe that fear God, to judge between us, with what equity can theſe men revile me and my opinion for looſe, profane and ungodly, whoſe only deſign is to ſet up Gods Ordinance amongſt us, that men and women may hereby acknowledge themſelves profeſſors, and diſciples of Chriſt, as they ought, by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his inſtitutions, <hi>(If you be my diſciples, keep my commandements)</hi> and in the mean time juſtifie themſelves in their own opinions, as moſt conſcientious and godly, that does but directly herein, as to the generality, go about the making void
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170195:77"/>the command of Chriſt by their tradition. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall break one of theſe leaſt commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and teach men ſo, ſhall be called leaſt in the kingdom of heaven.</hi> It is ſtrange, &amp; to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired (ſaies judicious <hi>Timſon</hi> in his latter book, <hi>p. 263.</hi>) that our preſſing to Chriſtian obſervance, ſhould have ſuch a hard ſenſe put upon it, as to be branded with looſneſs, when in all other duties, preſſing to obedience according to rule, is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted godlineſs, and holy ſtrictneſs. When <hi>Eraſtus</hi> (I find) is affirming that legal uncleanneſs only debarred the Jews from the holy things, and not moral, (which he ſaid was to be puniſht otherwiſe, as with priſon and death) <hi>Beza</hi> anſwers, <hi>At iniquiſſima lex Dei fuiſſet quod tam ſeverè ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum contactum puniret, ad ſcelera verò ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtè conniveret,</hi> as <hi>Eraſtus</hi> quotes him with thoſe words following, <hi>Exhorrui cum iſta tua legi, Conf. Theſ. 146.</hi> when others with <hi>Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> underſtand by <hi>Cutting off</hi> in the Law, <hi>an untimely death,</hi> to be inflicted by the Magiſtrate where the crime was open, or by God himſelf where it was ſecret, or the Magiſtrate neglected his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Lev. 20.4, 5. Gilleſpy</hi> anſwers, <hi>Then might the Moſaical lawes in ſuch texts,</hi> as Ex. <hi>30.38.</hi> Lev. <hi>7.20.</hi> Num. <hi>19.13.20. no leſſe than thoſe of</hi> Draco, <hi>be ſaid to have been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in blood, p. 53.</hi> (whereas indeed by the way, where the eſcape was ſo eaſy, the greater ſeverity threatned herein, ſhewed but the wiſdom of God, that none might willfully ever offer to incurre it:) So when I here fix my ſelf on the command of Chriſt, <hi>Doe this,</hi> to his Church, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of regenerate and unregenerate, and my adverſaries can come off here no way elſe, they make no more ado, but deny the command of God
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170195:77"/>to all but the regenerate only. A ſad thing in my apprehenſion, that men ſo pious, eminent, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, ſhould even be ready rather to fall foul on the very Laws of God himſelf, than to croſs or lay down their own conceptions. And yet I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member when <hi>Eraſtus</hi> is ſhewing many plain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing differences from Scripture, between legal and moral uncleanneſs in reference to the matter laſt mentioned; particularly, that legal uncleanneſs was ſuch, as by the appointment of God ſhould be liable to defile the holy things, &amp; ſo debarr men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, but there was no ſuch Law for moral: Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> takes him up thus, often, <hi>This is to diſpute with God, All this is mere cavilling at the wiſdom of God, Ch. Gov. p. 288.283.</hi> &amp;c. But whether there be any ingenuity or righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in ſuch replies; thoſe that read theſe contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry paſſages in his oppoſers, will judge and ſee eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (if men may have liberty to speak freely) who they be herein, if there be any, that doe but cavill indeed, and dispute with God. As for my part, I conceive that judgement which hath been given long ſince upon the dispute between <hi>Beza</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtus</hi> is good, that neither ſide is altogether in the right, but that they have divided the truth between them; which truth, ſo far as concerns me in this controverſie, I have endeavoured to find and lay down impartially in the preceding ſhe is, let o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe the like in other things that ſhall concern them.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>[7.]</hi> Whereas it is doubted whether <hi>Judas</hi> was preſent at the Sacrament, for which there is no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument commonly urged, can be conſiderable (this being matter of fact) but that only from <hi>Jo. 13.30.</hi> where it is ſaid <hi>he went out,</hi> There are two things, I conceive, convenient to be aſſerted here,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170195:78"/>in reference to the <hi>6</hi> Ch. of M. <hi>Coll.</hi> which he rightly ſtyles <hi>a digreſſion.</hi> The first is, That Jeſus Chriſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the received opinion of the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, did eat his Paſſeover on the ſame night with the Jews. This is irrefragably proved by thoſe texts, <hi>Mat. 14.12, 14, 15. Mat. 26.14 Lu. 22.7, 9, 11, 12.</hi> where I obſerve, <hi>1.</hi> It is ſaid to be the firſt day of the feaſt of unleavened bread, which <hi>Strictly</hi> began the night they kept the Paſſeover, after Sun-ſet, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing til Sun-ſet the next day: but <hi>Largely</hi> in our Saviors time they called the fourteenth day (becauſe it began at the evening therof enſuing) the firſt day of the feaſt, as the diſciples ſpeak here. <hi>2.</hi> It is likewiſe ſaid expreſly that it was the time the Paſso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>ought to be killed,</hi> &amp; <hi>was killed,</hi> ſo that there is no room for evaſion, whereas thoſe texts then, <hi>Io. 18.28.</hi> and <hi>Io. 19.14.</hi> are objected, that Chriſt was brought under <hi>Pilates</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>before the Paſſeover,</hi> there muſt on neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity be ſome ambiguity in theſe Texts or the other; But when <hi>Luke</hi> tells us it was the time the Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>ought to be killed,</hi> and <hi>Mat.</hi> and <hi>Mat.</hi> the <hi>time it was killed,</hi> there can be no evaſion here in the texts. I have quoted, without denyal of the truth thereof, and therefore the ambiguity is in the other objected; to wit, the Paſſover there which they were then preparing, is to be underſtood of the Paſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever of the Herd or Bullock, <hi>Deu. 16.2. 2 Chr. 30.24.</hi> and <hi>35.7, 8.</hi> and not of the Lamb they had already eaten over night. See <hi>Lyra</hi> on the place, and Dr. <hi>Eightfoots</hi> Temple Service, Chap. <hi>14.</hi> Sect. <hi>1.</hi> and Hand Glean. out of <hi>Exod.</hi> ſect. <hi>18.3.</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>the diſciples on this day came to Jeſus, ſaying, where wilt thou that we prepare for thee to eat the Paſſeover?</hi> Now how ſhould this be, if they punctually knew it not to be the day of the Jews? <hi>4.</hi> Thoſe diſciples he ſends to town
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170195:78"/>to prepare it, <hi>find a gueſs chamber already fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed</hi> according to Chriſts word; Now how ſhould that good man of the houſe have his room already furniſhed &amp; prepared for the Paſſeover, that knew nothing of Chriſts comming, if it were not now the time thereof according to the Jews? <hi>5.</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>At the feaſt Pilate</hi> uſed to releaſe to them a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, and he asked them, if they would be ſhould releaſe <hi>Jeſus;</hi> therefore it was not before the feaſt, but at the feaſt, <hi>Mat. 27.15. Lu. 23.17.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing is, that this being convinced, it will follow that this Supper in <hi>Jo. 13.</hi> was not Chriſts laſt Paſſeover Supper, for theſe reaſons, which I remember Dr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi> once ſhewed me in part of 0734 0 his <hi>Harmony</hi> yet in Manuſcript, or very much to this effect. <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe it is expreſſly ſaid ſo, v. <hi>1. Now before the feaſt of the Paſſeover. 2.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when <hi>Judas</hi> went out here, the diſciples thought he had gone out to buy ſomething againſt the feaſt, v. <hi>39.</hi> and therefore it was not at the feaſt. <hi>3.</hi> Becauſe when the even of that day was come (&amp; it is ſaid to be night here when <hi>Judas</hi> went out) wherein they eat the Paſsover it was holy, <hi>Ex. 12.16.</hi> &amp; there was then nothing to be bought or ſold, How then could the diſciples think <hi>Judas</hi> had gon out to buy ſomething againſt the feaſt, if it were that night it ſelf wherein nothing could be bought? <hi>4.</hi> The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil entred into <hi>Judas</hi> to ſet him on his villany, while the Paſſeover drew near, <hi>Lu. 22.1, 2, 3.</hi> that muſt needs be before the night it ſelf; but the devil entred Judas at the ſop in this Supper, <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Supper in <hi>John</hi> was before Chriſts laſt Supper. <hi>5.</hi> Becauſe there are many different paſſages (though accounted the ſame) at this ſupper in <hi>John,</hi> and Chriſts laſt Supper in the other Evangeliſts, which every one may eaſily multiply, that will be pleaſed exactly to read them. <hi>6.</hi> Becauſe there is not here one ſyllable
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170195:79"/>mentioned of the inſtitution of the Sacrament which was at Chriſts laſt Paſſeover Supper. <hi>7.</hi> Becauſe the exact reckoning we may find in Scripture of Chriſts laſt week before the Paſſeover may do much to inform us herein, which I conceive appeares thus. <hi>Six dayes before it,</hi> Jeſus came to <hi>Betha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> Jo. <hi>12.1. On the next day,</hi> he rides in triumph to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> v. <hi>12.</hi> and returns to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thany</hi> at night, <hi>Mar. 11.11. On the morrow,</hi> he went again thither to the Temple, <hi>Mar. 11.12, 15. When Even was come,</hi> he comes back as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, v. <hi>19. In the morning</hi> next, likewiſe he goes to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> v. <hi>20.27.</hi> and at night returns to the Mount of Olives, <hi>Luk. 21.37.</hi> where he lodges, we may conceive, in <hi>Bethany,</hi> as he was wont, for the next day, being now two dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Paſſeover, we find him there, comparing the Text following, <hi>Luk. 22.1, 2, 3, 4.</hi> with <hi>Matt. 26.2 — 14.</hi> and <hi>Mark 14.1, 3.</hi> And hereabouts, I conceive, for the two dayes follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he ſhelters himſelf, in his addreſſes for death, having departed purpoſely from the City to <hi>hide himſelf from them, Joh. 12.36.</hi> Now du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this time of his retirement, whereof the other Evangeliſts record nothing, we have the relation of <hi>John</hi> of this Supper, and many heavenly paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, in no leſs than <hi>4.</hi> or <hi>5.</hi> Chapters, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be thought one continued Speech or Sermon, as is commonly ſaid, if the words in <hi>ch. 14. v. ult.</hi> with <hi>ch. 18. v. 1.</hi> (likewiſe <hi>ch. 16.20.</hi>) be conſidered. Theſe diſcourſes then, meditations, tranſactions in <hi>ch. 13, 14, 15, 16, 17.</hi> (to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed) taking up theſe two dayes, the Paſſeover comes, Chriſt ſends two diſciples to the City to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it, <hi>Luke 22.7.</hi> Himſelf follows with the Twelve, <hi>Mar. 14.17.</hi> They all eat thereof, <hi>v.
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170195:79"/>20.</hi> After the hymn they go out, <hi>v. 26. Judas</hi> ſteals away to fetch the Officers, <hi>v. 43.</hi> Chriſt is apprehended, <hi>v. 46.</hi> The Jews ſit up all night up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him conſulting, (which appears by <hi>Peters</hi> Cocks crowing.) Early, as ſoon as it was light, <hi>Mat. 27.1. Jo. 18.28. Pilate</hi> is called up. The judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment haſtened and dispatcht. At<note n="*">As for that text, <hi>Jo.</hi> 19.14. Diſertè legitur <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, apud Petrum Alexandriae E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopum libello quem ſcripſit de Paſchate <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> nine a clock in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he is faſtned on the Croſs, <hi>Mar. 15.25.</hi> About twelve there comes the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe, <hi>Luke 23.44.</hi> After three, he gives up the ghoſt, <hi>Mar. 15.34, 37.</hi> is taken down and interred: In the grave he lies the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of that day, all the Jewiſh Sabbath, being the next, and part of the third, which by a Synecdoche of a part for the whole, is reckoned <hi>3.</hi> dayes, <hi>Mat. 16.21.</hi> Then he ariſes, being their firſt day of the week, <hi>Jo. 20.1.</hi> Is ſeen of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples for <hi>40</hi> dayes, <hi>Acts 1.3.</hi> and ſo aſcends to heaven, <hi>v. 9.</hi> Bleſſed be his name for ever.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>[8.]</hi> Wheras I have recorded a certain preſident from a neighbour, <hi>(Rejoynd. p. 240.)</hi> in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of that point, whether the Sacrament be a means of converſion, unto which others might be added, of ſome men eminent for the good they do in their places, who have told my ſelf the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke, as to the experiences of their own ſouls, which is much ſatisfying: I do think fit to take notice of thoſe two ſtories which Mr. <hi>Coll.</hi> mentions in oppoſition
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170195:80"/>hereunto, <hi>p. 14.</hi> Of two Women, the one under a Miniſter of his acquaintance, the other under Mr. <hi>Simmonds,</hi> who dying under carnal ſecurity, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed both their hardning to theſe mens admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to the Sacrament. Now theſe two ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and the like, I judge may be worthy very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious conſideration, ſomething contrary, and more likely, than that for which he brings them; for theſe Miniſters, I believe, were congregational men, or ſuch at leaſt who were more ſtrict than others as to their admiſſion, and it is this; (I pray God it may be judiciouſly laid to heart, whether it be ſo or no) that, while men pretend to have more pure communion, and ſo be more careful of ſeparating the vile from the precious, than others ordinarily, especially preſſing that this Ordinance belongs only to the regenerate, ſo that men muſt think themſelves ſo, when they come thither; It need be no wonder, unto any, that are but little acquainted with the fancies and temper of folks Spirits, that many weak people ſhould think well of their eſtates, that they are better than others being under theſe forms, and ſo grow ſecure, and harden, ſo long as ſuch holy Miniſters that refuſe others with ſuch cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, do receive them (as worthy perſons, and viſibly regenerate) to their Communions: whereas our former Miniſters, and we that ſay with Paul, <hi>Know ye not that all our Fathers were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the cloud, and drank of the rock, which rock was Chriſt?</hi> Know ye not that there is a common right, as to this outward priviledge of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances: ſo that we eſteem none of you better than your neighbours for your partaking hereof, <hi>we are of the circumciſion that worſhip God in the ſpirit, and have no confidence in the fleſh,</hi> or externals: I ſay, while we teach thus, we have
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170195:80"/>no occaſion to fear that any one ſhould grow spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually proud, or fall into ſecurity, thinking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves better than others for our admitting them to the Sacrament, any more than to other Ordinances, where we teach, and call upon them alike, to make uſe thereof unto repentance, &amp; acceptance of Chriſt, and not ſuppoſe them converted already, which lays the ground-work of folks hardning, if herein there be any. Whereas then Mr. <hi>Col.</hi> from <hi>Gilleſpy would fain know what fruit any godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters found of their former promiſcuous admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations?</hi> I anſwer, beſides the peace and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et of their people, which they now may wiſh, this fruit thereof they might have, that none of their congregations <hi>could bleſs themſelves in any ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed condition</hi> better than their fellows, for their outward participation of what was to be in common to all of them, the contrary whereof would by theſe men be faſtned on us; Even as all things (ſay the wiſe) have two handles, and every reaſon, a contrary reaſon.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>[9.]</hi> Whereas many worthy and pious Miniſters do think it would do well to bring their people to the giving ſome account to them of their faith and knowledge before the Sacrament, as a means for their future reformation; and there are ſome of their people that have taken, or be ready to take an occaſion from my opinion, to oppoſe their pious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours: I ſhall humbly declare thus much, for the ſakes of theſe people, that, Although I will not juſtifie any of theſe Miniſters that are more ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and fearful about the doing, than neglecting their office, and am perſwaded, that there is no Examination but of a mans own ſelf, can be preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as <hi>neceſſary</hi> to the Sacrament, yet do I both al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and reverence the piety, zeal and pains of many
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170195:81"/>Miniſters, that <hi>prudentially</hi> take occaſion hereby to <hi>look</hi> into the ſtate of their flocks, only for their admonition and inſtruction, without driving them from their duty; And I do bewail the frowardnes and offwardneſs of moſt unto ſo eaſie a ſubmiſſion, utterly diſliking at the bottom of my heart the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of ſuch Chriſtians, who either out of conſciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their own ignorance, or haughtineſs of their minds, will be contented to be deprived the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, rather than give an account of their faith to thoſe that ask it in the ſpirit of meekneſs, for their edification. Nay I do profeſs for my part, were I under the Presbytery, I ſhould moſt freely ſubject my ſelf to their trial, as being afraid to grieve the spirit of my Paſtor, (ſuppoſing him to require it meerly out of the tenderneſs of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience) and give example of obſtinacy to others; As alſo most eaſily believing that the people may do ill in refuſing examination, when the Miniſter does but ill too, in refuſing them therefore the Lords-Supper. <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves; for they watch for your ſouls, as they that muſt give account, that they may doe it with joy, and not with grief, for that is unprofitable for you.</hi> I ſpeak not this for ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tting up any power over mens conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, that are to be left free; but that I may ſo plead for Free-admiſſion, that I may not hinder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mens piety or reformation. To this end I could wiſh, that for the Ignorant, there were Catechiſts in the Church, and ſome prudent kind of Law for the bringing all ſuch to ſubmit to be catechized; and for the ſcandalous, that there were ſome autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritative way for the exerciſe of that moſt yielded, and leaſt practiſed duty of fraternal correption; let a man be profane, malicious, and injurious, I am
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170195:81"/>perſwaded one half hours ſerious rebuke of <hi>him</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore grave men, that ſhould awe him, would doe more towards his repentance, than many years kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping him from the Sacrament. If after this, the party does continue obſtinate, let him in the name of God be proceeded againſt by Church-cenſure or Excommunication; A thing doubtleſs, which if the main truth in my bookes I drive at firſt, were well eſtabliſht, would have its ſeaſon to be preſſed.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>[10.]</hi> Whereas I find that many of the moſt holy Chriſtians have their faces ſet againſt our mixt Communions, and that general way of Unity I look at, the pantings and breathings of whoſe spirits af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter holineſs and purity, I cannot but reverence, though I think them led more by their preſent affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, than ſoundeſs of Judgment, It is my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and reſolution, having now propoſed my thoughts, rather than grieve and exaſperate them any more, to leave the Controverſy; ſo that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome more than ordinary urgent reaſon be to the contrary, which is not live to be, I ſhall not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage perſonally with any of them agen about the ſame, but ſhall commit my cauſe to the Lord, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeeching him to pardon me all my failings that have been in it, and perſwading my ſelf that if there be any thing uſefull for the Church in what I have written, ſome one or other that are friends of truth, will ſtand by her in a time and ſeaſon fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for it, <hi>And farther by theſe my Son be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed, of making many books there is no end, and much ſtudy is a wearineſs to the fleſh; Let us hear the concluſion of the matter, Fear God and keep his commandements, for this is the whole of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Froome, <date>May <hi>26. 1656:</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. H.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
